<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Research Group Information Management @ Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin</title>
<link>https://infomgnt.org/index.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://infomgnt.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Research Group Information Management @ Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin</description>
<generator>quarto-1.3.450</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 23:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Neue Informations- und Lernmaterialien aus dem Projekt OA Datenpraxis</title>
  <dc:creator>Dorothea Strecker</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Sophia Dörner</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-12-03-neue-informations-und-lernmaterialien-aus-dem-projekt-oa-datenpraxis/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Das Projekt <a href="https://oa-datenpraxis.de">OA Datenpraxis</a> verfolgt das Ziel, die Open-Access-Transformation in Deutschland voranzubringen, indem der Umgang mit Publikations- und Kostendaten untersucht und unterstützt wird.</p>
<p>Das Projektteam hat nun Informations- und Lernmaterialien zu Monitoringaktivitäten mit offenen Datenquellen veröffentlicht. Diese Materialien sind orientiert an den “Kompetenzprofilen für die Open-Access-Transformation” des Projektes <a href="https://transform2open.de">Transform2Open</a> <span class="citation" data-cites="shelly_competency_2025">(Shelly and Höhnow 2025)</span> und richten sich an Menschen, die an wissenschaftlichen Einrichtungen für Open Access verantwortlich sind.</p>
<p>Zu den neuen Materialien zählen interaktive R-Notebooks, die als Selbstlernmaterialien auf der Projektwebseite veröffentlicht sind. Die Notebooks zeigen, wie offene Datenquellen für die Analyse von Publikationsaufkommen und -kosten genutzt werden können und stellen interaktive Übungen bereit, um einzelne Analyseschritte selbstständig auszuprobieren. Vorkenntnisse oder eine Installation von Software sind nicht erforderlich. Die Notebooks wurden vor Veröffentlichung durch Personen mit unterschiedlichen Vorkenntnissen getestet. Sie finden sich unter:</p>
<p>Open Access Monitoring with OpenAlex: <a href="https://oa-datenpraxis.de/OpenAlex.html" class="uri">https://oa-datenpraxis.de/OpenAlex.html</a> Open Access Cost Monitoring with OpenAPC: <a href="https://oa-datenpraxis.de/OpenAPC.html" class="uri">https://oa-datenpraxis.de/OpenAPC.html</a></p>
<p>Weiterhin wurde im Projekt eine Einführung in das Thema Open-Access-Monitoring und Open Research Information für Menschen in Bibliotheken erstellt. Diese Einführung wurde als Teil der “LIBER Digital Scholarship &amp; Data Science Topic Guides for Library Professionals” veröffentlicht <span class="citation" data-cites="strecker_open_2025">(Strecker and Dörner 2025)</span>.</p>
<p>LIBER Digital Scholarship &amp; Data Science Topic Guides for Library Professionals - Open Access Monitoring and Open Research Information: <a href="https://doi.org/10.23636/dwcn-x827" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.23636/dwcn-x827</a></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-12-03-neue-informations-und-lernmaterialien-aus-dem-projekt-oa-datenpraxis/liber_guide.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Screenshot des LIBER Digital Scholarship &amp; Data Science Topic Guides “Open Access Monitoring and Open Research Information”</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Beide Materialien, die Notebooks und der Digital Scholarship &amp; Data Science Topic Guide, liegen auf Englisch vor und sind unter einer freien Lizenz veröffentlicht.</p>
<p>Rückfragen können Sie gerne jederzeit an das Projektteam von OA Datenpraxis richten: info.oa-datenpraxis@listserv.dfn.de</p>
<p>Weitere Informationen über die Forschungsgruppe Information Managementan der Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin, einem der Partner im Projekt, finden sich auf der <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">offiziellen Website der Gruppe</a>. Informationen zum Arbeitsbereich Scholarly Communication Analytics an der SUB Göttingen finden sich u. a. auf <a href="https://subugoe.github.io" class="uri">https://subugoe.github.io</a>.</p>
<p>Dieser Text – mit Ausnahme von Zitaten und anderweitig gekennzeichneten Abschnitten – steht unter der <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
<div id="ref-shelly_competency_2025" class="csl-entry">
Shelly, Joshua, and Tobias Höhnow. 2025. <span>“Competency <span>Profiles</span> for the <span>Open</span> <span>Access</span> <span>Transformation</span>.”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.16979893">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.16979893</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-strecker_open_2025" class="csl-entry">
Strecker, Dorothea, and Sophia Dörner. 2025. <span>“Open <span>Access</span> <span>Monitoring</span> and <span>Open</span> <span>Research</span> <span>Information</span>.”</span> Edited by Nora McGregor. LIBER. <a href="https://doi.org/10.23636/dwcn-x827">https://doi.org/10.23636/dwcn-x827</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{strecker2025,
  author = {Strecker, Dorothea and Dörner, Sophia},
  title = {Neue {Informations-} Und {Lernmaterialien} Aus Dem {Projekt}
    {OA} {Datenpraxis}},
  date = {2025-12-03},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/z46ht-zm446},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-strecker2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Strecker, Dorothea, and Sophia Dörner. 2025. <span>“Neue Informations-
Und Lernmaterialien Aus Dem Projekt OA Datenpraxis.”</span> December 3,
2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/z46ht-zm446">https://doi.org/10.59350/z46ht-zm446</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-12-03-neue-informations-und-lernmaterialien-aus-dem-projekt-oa-datenpraxis/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-12-03-neue-informations-und-lernmaterialien-aus-dem-projekt-oa-datenpraxis/liber_guide.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="172" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>New Guide on Publication and Cost Monitoring through Institutional Repositories</title>
  <dc:creator>Lisa Matthias</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Christopher Onzie Khamis</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-11-26-new-guide-on-publication-and-cost-monitoring/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>We are pleased to announce the publication of our fourth guide from the BMFTR-funded (Federal Ministry for Research, Technology and Space) project “Professionalisierung der Open-Access-Repositorien-Infrastruktur in Deutschland (Pro OAR DE)”: “Publikations- und Kostenmonitoring: Handlungsfeld für institutionelle Open-Access Repositorien” (available in German only).</p>
<p>Matthias, L., Pampel, H., Khamis, C. O., &amp; Rothfritz, L. (2025). Publikations- und Kostenmonitoring: Handlungsfeld für institutionelle Open-Access Repositorien. Pro OAR DE Handreichung. Zenodo. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.17357984" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.17357984</a></p>
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-11-26-new-guide-on-publication-and-cost-monitoring/Blogpost_Monitoring_Handreichung.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>This guide documents the outcomes of our networking forum “<a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/infomanagement/events/prooarde-monitoring">Publikations- und Kostenmonitoring mit institutionellen Repositorien</a>,” held on March 10, 2025, with 100 Open Access professionals from across Germany. Drawing on their collaborative work, the guide offers concrete, practice-based recommendations for advancing publication and cost monitoring through institutional repositories. Experts Dirk Pieper and Julia Bartlewski (Universität Bielefeld), as well as Colin Sippl and Gernot Deinzer (Universität Regensburg), presented concrete action options for publication and cost monitoring. Building on these presentations, participants worked together in a “world café” setting to share institutional experiences and develop practical approaches to common challenges. Presentation slides are available <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15056242">online</a>. The guide synthesizes these collective insights into practical recommendations organized around five critical areas for institutional repository management:</p>
<section id="definitions-of-publication-and-cost-data" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="definitions-of-publication-and-cost-data">Definitions of Publication and Cost Data</h3>
<p>Publication data encompasses all information about published scientific works, including authors, titles, abstracts, and persistent identifiers (PIDs) such as DOIs. Cost data refers to the financial aspects of publication, such as publication fees, processing fees, and value-added tax. The diversity of categories, lack of glossaries, currency, completeness, and inconsistencies between disciplines were identified as central challenges. Clear definitions and collection of these data are essential for effective monitoring. Different departments within an institution, such as libraries, finance departments, and university management, have varying requirements for this information. Close collaboration and regular communication are therefore crucial to establish efficient and transparent workflows.</p>
</section>
<section id="integration-of-external-data-sources" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="integration-of-external-data-sources">Integration of External Data Sources</h3>
<p>The integration of various data sources into repositories poses significant technical challenges. A fundamental issue is avoiding duplicates, which regularly occur during data aggregation from multiple sources. Services like OpenAIRE can help aggregate data and remove duplicates, though the completeness and effectiveness of these functions remain under continuous development. Another challenge involves integrating proprietary research information systems (CRIS). The lack of standardization and limited interoperability of these systems significantly complicate automated data exchange. Many steps still need to be performed manually, limiting both scalability and data quality. In addition to establishing standard interfaces, participants recommended the data service <a href="https://info.oa-deepgreen.de/en/">DeepGreen</a> for Open Access and secondary publications, noting that data verification workflows remain necessary.</p>
</section>
<section id="partners-for-cooperation-within-the-institution-and-beyond" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="partners-for-cooperation-within-the-institution-and-beyond">Partners for Cooperation within the Institution and Beyond</h3>
<p>Successful collaboration requires clear role descriptions and appropriate involvement of various stakeholders within the institution, such as faculties, libraries, IT departments, financial controlling, and other administrative units. Cross-institutional cooperation, including state initiatives, information infrastructure networks, and standardization projects, is equally important. Regular exchange with all stakeholders helps ensure that strategic considerations are coordinated and consistently developed. To this end, participants recommended the strategic selection of cost monitoring tools based on established standards and consistent alignment with best practices from other institutions.</p>
</section>
<section id="standards-for-monitoring" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="standards-for-monitoring">Standards for Monitoring</h3>
<p>Establishing uniform standards for recording and evaluating publication and cost data is essential. A controlled vocabulary for different data categories, such as cost and publication types, can improve the comparability of monitoring results. Projects like COAR and openCost offer promising approaches for developing such standards. Another complex area is the representation of costs for individual publications versus contract costs. Linking individual publications to overarching contracts poses an additional hurdle, particularly in transformative agreements where publication costs cannot be directly assigned to individual articles. To address the challenges posed by currently missing standards, participants recommended several practical solutions: systematic metadata comparisons between different sources, clear documentation of cost types, and the identification of net and gross amounts.</p>
</section>
<section id="workflows-within-the-institution-and-the-role-of-the-repository" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="workflows-within-the-institution-and-the-role-of-the-repository">Workflows within the Institution and the Role of the Repository</h3>
<p>Integrating publication and cost monitoring into existing institutional processes requires close cooperation between different stakeholders and departments. The use of different systems for various aspects of publication and cost monitoring, combined with heterogeneous cost data, pose central challenges. Participants recommended integrating all relevant functions into a single system, as this would make the processes significantly more efficient. The traditionally separate areas of cataloging, repository operation, and cost recording are gradually converging but remain far from full integration. Close cooperation between these areas for comprehensive cost and research reporting is seen as essential.</p>
</section>
<section id="additional-challenges" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="additional-challenges">Additional Challenges</h3>
<p>Beyond the challenges already mentioned, several additional issues can arise when implementing publication and cost monitoring systems. Communication with various stakeholders is often complex and can lead to uncertainties regarding fundamental questions, such as eligible publication costs and the role of the corresponding author. The continuous training of researchers and other involved parties also presents a challenge. Information events and training sessions are time-consuming to prepare and must be offered regularly. The high resource requirements for the comprehensive recording of all publications and their associated costs were also identified as challenges. The transition of cost management from Excel-based solutions to repositories or bibliographic systems poses a technical hurdle. Recommended solutions include direct presentations in scientific working groups, information offerings at events for early career researchers, and positioning as a central point of contact for publication-related matters.</p>
<hr>
<p>This guide provides a foundation for continued professional exchange. Repository operators, libraries, and institutional decision-makers will find valuable insights for establishing effective publication and cost monitoring workflows within their institutions.</p>
<p>We extend our sincere thanks to all forum participants who contributed their expertise and experience to this collaborative effort. We welcome your feedback and look forward to continuing this important dialogue as we collectively strengthen the Open Access repository landscape.</p>
<p>For more information about Pro OAR DE and our upcoming activities, please visit our <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/infomanagement/projekte/pro-oar-de">website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labeled sections – is licensed under the CC BY 4.0 DEED.</p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
<div id="ref-noauthor_deepgreen_nodate" class="csl-entry">
<span>“<span>DeepGreen</span>.”</span> n.d. Accessed August 18, 2025. <a href="https://info.oa-deepgreen.de/en/">https://info.oa-deepgreen.de/en/</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-matthias_publikations-_2025" class="csl-entry">
Matthias, Lisa, Heinz Pampel, Christopher Onzie Khamis, and Laura Rothfritz. 2025. <span>“Publikations- Und <span>Kostenmonitoring</span>: <span>Handlungsfeld</span> Für Institutionelle <span>Open</span>-<span>Access</span>-<span>Repositorien</span>. <span>Pro</span> <span>OAR</span> <span>DE</span> <span>Handreichung</span>.”</span> Zenodo. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.17357984">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.17357984</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-matthias_pro_2025" class="csl-entry">
Matthias, Lisa, Dirk Pieper, Julia Bartlewski, Colin Sippl, and Gernot Deinzer. 2025. <span>“Pro <span>OAR</span> <span>DE</span> <span>Vernetzungsforum</span>: <span>Publikations</span>- Und <span>Kostenmonitoring</span> Mit Institutionellen <span>Repositorien</span>,”</span> March. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15056242">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15056242</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{matthias2025,
  author = {Matthias, Lisa and Pampel, Heinz and Onzie Khamis,
    Christopher},
  title = {New {Guide} on {Publication} and {Cost} {Monitoring} Through
    {Institutional} {Repositories}},
  date = {2025-11-26},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/rhe8t-bh241},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-matthias2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Matthias, Lisa, Heinz Pampel, and Christopher Onzie Khamis. 2025.
<span>“New Guide on Publication and Cost Monitoring Through
Institutional Repositories.”</span> November 26, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/rhe8t-bh241">https://doi.org/10.59350/rhe8t-bh241</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-11-26-new-guide-on-publication-and-cost-monitoring/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-11-26-new-guide-on-publication-and-cost-monitoring/Blogpost_Monitoring_Handreichung.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Workshop Report: Resilience in Times of Crisis - Strengthening Open Science Against Geopolitical Pressures</title>
  <dc:creator>Laura Rothfritz</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Dorothea Strecker</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-11-19-workshop-report-resilience-in-time-of-crisis/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>On November 6 2025, we participated in the Workshop “Resilience in Times of Crisis: Strengthening Open Science Against Geopolitical Pressures” at the CWTS in Leiden.</p>
<p>The workshop made reference to the UNESCO Recommendation on Open Science <span class="citation" data-cites="noauthor_unesco_2021">(<span>“<span>UNESCO</span> <span>Recommendation</span> on <span>Open</span> <span>Science</span>”</span> 2021)</span>, which presented an extensive and inclusive vision for Open Science when they were published in 2021. In the geopolitical climate of 2025, the values in the UNESCO Recommendation on Open Science are threatened. Throughout the day, 20-30 participants discussed influences of geopolitics on Open Science, areas that require (more) awareness, and strategies to make Open Science more resilient.</p>
<p>In her keynote, <a href="https://www.library.upenn.edu/staff/lynda-kellam">Lynda Kellam</a> from the University of Pennsylvania Libraries introduced the <a href="https://www.datarescueproject.org">Data Rescue Project</a>. Following the keynote, invited speakers offered their thoughts on the resilience of Open Science practices and infrastructures. <a href="https://pure.royalholloway.ac.uk/en/persons/hugh-shanahan/">Hugh Shanahan</a> from Royal Holloway, University of London talked about factors that can put preprint servers at risk: the strong involvement of US institutions and a reliance on commercial internet service providers. <a href="https://www.molly-hardy.com">Molly Hardy</a> from the Library Innovation Lab at Harvard Law School introduced the <a href="https://lil.law.harvard.edu/our-work/public-data-project/">Public Data Project</a>, which applies curation practices to data rescue initiatives. <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/infomanagement/teaminfomanagement">Laura Rothfritz</a> from our research group at the Berlin School of Library and Information Science at Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin presented results from her PhD thesis on the Data Rescue movement in 2017 and 2018 - read more about her contribution below. <a href="https://geotraces-gp15.com/joseph-gum/">Joseph Gum</a> discussed potential business models of open data infrastructures and risks associated with them. He also presented the <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15208172">Repository Crisis Scorecard</a>, a tool that can be used to assess the resilience of a repository during a crisis. <a href="https://www.uu.nl/staff/JMBosman">Jeroen Bosman</a> from Utrecht University offered a categorization of threats to Open Science as well as strategies to increase resilience. His slides are published <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.17558233">here</a>.</p>
<section id="laura-rothfritz---rescuing-data-resisting-loss" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="laura-rothfritz---rescuing-data-resisting-loss">Laura Rothfritz - Rescuing data, resisting loss</h2>
<p>In her lightning talk, Laura shared results from her PhD research <span class="citation" data-cites="rothfritzWhatHappensWhen2025">(Rothfritz 2025)</span> which focuses on the first Data Rescue movement in 2017/2018 and asked when actions that feel resilient actually build resilience. Drawing on interview material she has collected for her thesis, she framed earlier data rescue efforts as “emergency curation”, which she defines as a form of first aid data duplication. This practice offered relief from fears around supposed data deletion but often produced redundancies of datasets without their contextual information, leading to unsustainable data practices. In her research, and in this talk, she is making a point to stress the importance of the affective consequences this sort of data activism might have, defined as such by my interviewees. These consequences range from feeling empowered and regaining agency in (politically) taxing times, to overwhelm and burnout.</p>
<p>In her research, Laura proposes the concept of anticipatory maintenance, defined as a preventive, future-oriented form of (infrastructural) care that turns imagined disruption into present routines aimed at sustaining continuity under uncertainty. She argues that in large parts this is what both iterations of the Data Rescue movement, in 2017/2018 and 2024/2025 respectively, might be seen as. In line with Jackson <span class="citation" data-cites="jacksonRethinkingRepair2014a">(2014)</span> and Rubio <span class="citation" data-cites="rubioIntroductionAvowingFragility2025c">(2025)</span>, she draws on broken-world thinking, which can be defined as a mindset of thinking with fragility and treating it as a normal, relational condition we live with. If fragility is seen as ordinary, then resilience is not a set goal but should be understood as a practice that must continually be negotiated. This is where future-oriented anticipatory maintenance might help with feeling resilient and simultaneously building resilience.</p>
<p>The slides from Laura’s presentation are available on Zendodo at:</p>
<p>Rothfritz, L. (2025, November 6). Rescuing Data, Resisting Loss - Emergency Curation, Anticipatory Maintenance And The Limits Of Feeling Resilient. Resilience in times of crisis: Strengthening Open Science against geopolitical pressures, Leiden, Netherlands. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.17570709" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.17570709</a></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-11-19-workshop-report-resilience-in-time-of-crisis/2025_Leiden.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Laura Rothfritz presenting at the workshop “Resilience in Times of Crisis: Strengthening Open Science Against Geopolitical Pressures”</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Further information about our research group can be found on our <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labelled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
<div id="ref-jacksonRethinkingRepair2014a" class="csl-entry">
Jackson, Steven J. 2014. <span>“Rethinking <span>Repair</span>.”</span> In <em>Media <span>Technologies</span></em>, edited by Tarleton Gillespie, Pablo J. Boczkowski, and Kirsten A. Foot, 221–40. The MIT Press. <a href="https://doi.org/10.7551/mitpress/9042.003.0015">https://doi.org/10.7551/mitpress/9042.003.0015</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-rothfritzWhatHappensWhen2025" class="csl-entry">
Rothfritz, Laura. 2025. <span>“What Happens When Public Data Infrastructures Aren’t Save? <span>A</span> Look at Past and Current Developments in the <span>US</span> – <span>Research Group Information Management</span> @ <span>Humboldt-Universität</span> Zu <span>Berlin</span>.”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/6g3km-9w70">https://doi.org/10.59350/6g3km-9w70</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-rubioIntroductionAvowingFragility2025c" class="csl-entry">
Rubio, Fernando Domínguez. 2025. <span>“Introduction: <span>Avowing Fragility</span>.”</span> In <em>Fragilities: <span>Essays</span> on the <span>Politics</span>, <span>Ethics</span>, and <span>Aesthetics</span> of <span>Maintenance</span> and <span>Repair</span></em>. The MIT Press. <a href="https://doi.org/10.7551/mitpress/14227.001.0001">https://doi.org/10.7551/mitpress/14227.001.0001</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-noauthor_unesco_2021" class="csl-entry">
<span>“<span>UNESCO</span> <span>Recommendation</span> on <span>Open</span> <span>Science</span>.”</span> 2021. UNESCO. <a href="https://doi.org/10.54677/MNMH8546">https://doi.org/10.54677/MNMH8546</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{rothfritz2025,
  author = {Rothfritz, Laura and Strecker, Dorothea},
  title = {Workshop {Report:} {Resilience} in {Times} of {Crisis} -
    {Strengthening} {Open} {Science} {Against} {Geopolitical}
    {Pressures}},
  date = {2025-11-19},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/js8da-36a98},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-rothfritz2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Rothfritz, Laura, and Dorothea Strecker. 2025. <span>“Workshop Report:
Resilience in Times of Crisis - Strengthening Open Science Against
Geopolitical Pressures.”</span> November 19, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/js8da-36a98">https://doi.org/10.59350/js8da-36a98</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-11-19-workshop-report-resilience-in-time-of-crisis/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-11-19-workshop-report-resilience-in-time-of-crisis/2025_Leiden.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="108" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Institutional Repositories and Secondary Publication: A New Guide from Pro OAR DE</title>
  <dc:creator>Lisa Matthias</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Christopher Onzie Khamis</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-11-06-institutional-repositories-and-secondary-publication/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>We are pleased to announce the publication of our third guide from the BMFTR-funded (Federal Ministry for Research, Technology and Space) project “Professionalisierung der Open-Access-Repositorien-Infrastruktur in Deutschland (Pro OAR DE)”: “Zweitveröffentlichung: Handlungsfeld für institutionelle Open-Access-Repositorien” (available in German only).</p>
<p>Matthias, L. Pampel, H., Khamis, C. O. &amp; Rothfritz, L. (2025). <em>Zweitveröffentlichung: Handlungsfeld für institutionelle Open-Access-Repositorien</em>. Handreichung. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.16810750" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.16810750</a></p>
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-11-06-institutional-repositories-and-secondary-publication/Blogpost_Zweitveröffentlichung_Handreichung.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>This guide documents the outcomes of our networking forum <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/infomanagement/events/prooarde-zweitveroeffentlichung">“Institutionelle Repositorien und Zweitveröffentlichung”</a> (Institutional Repositories and Secondary Publication), held on January 13, 2025, which brought together nearly 100 Open Access professionals from across Germany.</p>
<p>Experts Sonja Härkönen (Universität Augsburg) and Tomasz Stompor (Kooperativer Bibliotheksverbund Berlin-Brandenburg) presented concrete strategies for secondary publication. Webinar participants then collaborated in thematic working groups, exchanging institutional experiences and co-developing practical solutions to common challenges. The presentation slides are available <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14725629">online</a>.</p>
<p>The guide consolidates these collective insights into practical recommendations organized around six essential areas for repository operations:</p>
<section id="supporting-researchers" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="supporting-researchers">1. Supporting Researchers</h2>
<p>A central challenge identified was bridging the gap between researcher needs and library requirements, particularly regarding manuscript versions. While libraries typically work with Author Accepted Manuscripts (AAMs), researchers often prefer using the Version of Record (VoR) for secondary publication. Low awareness of institutional repositories awareness frequently prevents researchers from considering secondary publication altogether. Participants recommended strengthening the institutional presence of Open Access officers as central contact points, integrating Open Access topics into training programs, developing efficient workflows through connection with existing structures, and implementing automated notification systems for publication opportunities. Participants emphasized that secondary publication should not burden researchers but rather serve as a professional library service that minimizes administrative and technical effort.</p>
</section>
<section id="open-access-policies-of-funding-organizations" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="open-access-policies-of-funding-organizations">2. Open Access Policies of Funding Organizations</h2>
<p>Participants stressed the need for clear communication and comprehensible guidelines. They called for concrete frameworks for secondary publication, including a maximum embargo period of 12 months and use of the VoR. Sustainable availability should be ensured through long-term archiving in certified repositories. Given the inconsistent success with implementation, participants discussed whether stronger political mandates from federal and state governments could foster a more consistent Open Access landscape.</p>
</section>
<section id="publisher-open-access-policies" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="publisher-open-access-policies">3. Publisher Open Access Policies</h2>
<p>Participants identified core elements for transparent publisher policies: clear definitions of permitted secondary publication strategies, permissible manuscript versions and publication venues, and precise specifications regarding embargo periods, licensing conditions, and citation requirements. For legal certainty, they recommended documenting each publisher policy through screenshots or PDF exports. Practical tools and direct publisher contact were also recommended. To optimize processes, participants suggested verifying upfront whether authors possess the required manuscript version. Active networking in the <a href="https://open-access.network/vernetzen/digitale-fokusgruppen/fokusgruppe-zweitveroeffentlichen">open-access.network focus group on secondary publication</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="workflows-and-opportunities-for-automation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="workflows-and-opportunities-for-automation">4. Workflows and Opportunities for Automation</h2>
<p>Participants emphasized aligning secondary publication processes with institutional priorities, particularly to promote Green Open Access. Technical solutions highlighted included open-source applications and automated interfaces to rights-checking platforms. For capturing publications, they recommended ORCID profiles, subject database exports, and specialized library tools. Participants prioritized standardization as a critical prerequisite for automation: routine procedures, email templates, and centralized documentation systems for publisher policies can significantly streamline workflows. They also recommended anchoring mandatory submission of accepted manuscript versions in institutional publication policies.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-role-of-green-open-access-in-the-open-access-transformation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-role-of-green-open-access-in-the-open-access-transformation">5. The Role of Green Open Access in the Open Access Transformation</h2>
<p>Participants discussed resource challenges, observing that Gold Open Access tends to absorb most institutional capacity, leaving Green Open Access to be managed as a secondary priority. Nevertheless, some institutions reported successful Green publication pathways supported by technical solutions such as self-submission systems with rights transfer options and automated reminders. Despite declining significance due to transformative agreements, participants emphasized the strengths of the Green route: cost-free access would enable all institutions to participate in the Open Access movement, especially for older publications with restricted access. The increase in secondary publication could be strategically leveraged in future publisher negotiations, with the role of preprints considered in a differentiated, discipline-specific manner.</p>
</section>
<section id="reform-of-secondary-publication-rights" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reform-of-secondary-publication-rights">6. Reform of Secondary Publication Rights</h2>
<p>Participants called for secondary publication of publisher versions under short embargo periods with CC BY licenses. The current 12-month embargo period was criticized as too long, as was the difficult-to-verify 50% funding clause in the German Copyright Act (<a href="https://www.gesetze-im-internet.de/urhg/__38.html">UrhG § 38 Abs. 4</a>). They recommended a multi-step approach to rights verification, systematic documentation of publisher policies, and interpreting them in favor of authors. Library and institutional leadership should be encouraged to actively utilize secondary publication rights, particularly given the difficulty of obtaining early manuscript versions in disciplines without established preprint cultures.</p>
</section>
<section id="additional-challenges" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="additional-challenges">7. Additional Challenges</h2>
<p>Participants identified technical challenges in the interaction between research information systems and repositories, particularly the need to distinguish between primary and secondary publications using metadata. Other core challenges included legal consultation, compliance with funding requirements, and the resource-intensive article acquisition process. Recommended solutions included increased networking for exchanging best practices, workflow automation, and adequate staffing capacity. Participants particularly emphasized the untapped potential of UrhG § 38 Abs. 4 and the need for systematic public outreach regarding secondary publication services.</p>
<hr>
<p>This guide provides a foundation for continued professional exchange on secondary publication practices. Repository operators, libraries, and institutional decision-makers will find valuable insights for developing effective secondary publication workflows that support both researchers and institutional Open Access goals. We extend our sincere thanks to all forum participants who contributed their expertise and experience to this collaborative effort. We welcome your feedback and look forward to continuing this important dialogue as we collectively strengthen the Open Access repository landscape in Germany and beyond. BTW: We just published a study in the Journal of the Association for Information Science and Technology (JASIST): <a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/asi.70016" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1002/asi.70016</a>. In this systematic review, we examine the key challenges institutional repositories face in advancing Open Access and supporting the dissemination of scholarly work. These include issues of strategic alignment, sustainable funding, staffing, technology, and researcher engagement. Our findings underscore the importance of integrating IRs with institutional strategies, strengthening professional and technical capacities, and ensuring consistent support to reinforce IRs as vital components of the Open Science ecosystem. For more information about Pro OAR DE and our upcoming activities, please visit our <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/infomanagement/projekte/pro-oar-de">website</a>. This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labeled sections – is licensed under the CC BY 4.0 DEED.</p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
<div id="ref-Matthias.etal+shorttitle22+yearu" class="csl-entry">
Matthias, Lisa, Heinz Pampel, Christopher Onzie Khamis, and Laura Rothfritz. 2025. <span>“Zweitveröffentlichung: Handlungsfeld für institutionelle Open-Access-Repositorien. Pro OAR DE Handreichung.”</span> Zenodo. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.16810750">https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.16810750</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Rothfritz.etal+shorttitle22+yearh" class="csl-entry">
Rothfritz, Laura, Lisa Matthias, Heinz Pampel, and Marcel Wrzesinski. 2025. <span>“Current Challenges and Future Directions for Institutional Repositories: <span>A</span> Systematic Literature Review. <span>An Annual Review</span> of <span>Information Science</span> and <span>Technology</span> (<span>ARIST</span>) Paper.”</span> <em>Journal of the Association for Information Science and Technology</em>, August, asi.70016. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/asi.70016">https://doi.org/10.1002/asi.70016</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Wrzesinski.etal+shorttitle22+yearq" class="csl-entry">
Wrzesinski, Marcel, Sonja Härkönen, and Tomasz Stompor. 2025. <span>“Vernetzungsforum: Institutionelle Repositorien und Zweitveröffentlichung,”</span> January. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.14725629">https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.14725629</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{matthias2025,
  author = {Matthias, Lisa and Pampel, Heinz and Onzie Khamis,
    Christopher},
  title = {Institutional {Repositories} and {Secondary} {Publication:}
    {A} {New} {Guide} from {Pro} {OAR} {DE}},
  date = {2025-11-06},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/k8v8h-evr11},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-matthias2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Matthias, Lisa, Heinz Pampel, and Christopher Onzie Khamis. 2025.
<span>“Institutional Repositories and Secondary Publication: A New Guide
from Pro OAR DE.”</span> November 6, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/k8v8h-evr11">https://doi.org/10.59350/k8v8h-evr11</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-11-06-institutional-repositories-and-secondary-publication/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-11-06-institutional-repositories-and-secondary-publication/Blogpost_Zweitveröffentlichung_Handreichung.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Praktiken und Infrastrukturen des Open-Access-Monitorings</title>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Lisa-Marie Stein</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Bernhard Mittermaier</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Dorothea Strecker</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Bianca Schweighofer</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Gernot Deinzer</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-10-27-praktiken-und-infrastrukturen-des-open-access-monioring/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Am 19. September 2025 führten die DFG-geförderten Projekte <a href="https://oa-datenpraxis.de">OA Datenpraxis</a>, <a href="https://www.opencost.de/projekt/">openCost</a> und <a href="https://www.transform2open.de">Transform2Open</a> gemeinsam den Workshop „Praktiken und Infrastrukturen des Open-Access-Monitorings“ auf den Open-Access-Tagen 2025 durch <span class="citation" data-cites="pampel_praktiken_2025">(Pampel et al. 2025)</span>. Nach einer kurzen Vorstellung der beteiligten Projekte diskutierten mehr als 30 Teilnehmende aktuelle Fragestellungen des Open-Access-Monitorings im Format World Café. Dabei wurden die folgenden Handlungsfelder in den Blick genommen: (1) die Stärkung der Standardisierung im Bereich des Monitorings, (2) die Förderung von Transparenzinitiativen in diesem Bereich, (3) die Weiterentwicklung der Nachnutzungsmöglichkeiten offener Daten – auch im Kontext der Barcelona Declaration.</p>
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-10-27-praktiken-und-infrastrukturen-des-open-access-monioring/oat.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<section id="standardisierung" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="standardisierung">Standardisierung</h2>
<p>An der Station „Standardisierung“ diskutierten die Teilnehmenden, welchen Herausforderungen sie im Hinblick auf die Vereinheitlichung von Prozessen in ihren Einrichtungen begegnen. Dabei zeigte sich, dass über klassische Publikationsformate hinaus auch weitere Objekte und Formen zunehmend relevant werden. Genannt wurden u. a. Konferenzbeiträge, die Publikationsgebühren in der Teilnahmegebühr enthalten, Einreichungsgebühren, Beiträge zu Diamond-Open-Access-Formaten sowie experimentelle Langform-Publikationen und Bücher im weiteren Sinne. Für letztere wurden zusätzliche Kostenaspekte wie Layout, Lektorat, Videoschnitt, Programmierung (z. B. für Publikationswebseiten), Archivierung oder Disseminationsgebühren hervorgehoben. Dies verdeutlicht, dass je nach Disziplin spezifische Erfahrungen und Bedarfe existieren, die für die Weiterentwicklung eines Metadatenstandards zur Erfassung von Publikationskosten berücksichtigt werden müssen. In Bezug auf die Kostendatenerfassung wurde deutlich, dass an vielen Einrichtungen noch erheblicher Unterstützungsbedarf besteht. Genannt wurden insbesondere die Herausforderung, Daten aus unterschiedlichen Quellen abzugleichen, die Weiterentwicklung bestehender Systeme oder Kostenmodule sowie Fragen des Rechtemanagements. Diskutiert wurde auch die Nutzung einrichtungsindividueller Tabellen und Formate, etwa im Kontext der Ablieferung an OpenAPC, sowie die Notwendigkeit, community-geleitet gemeinsame Standards für mehr Effizienz und Vergleichbarkeit zu entwickeln. Der Bedarf an Standardisierung wurde somit klar als Mittel zur individuellen Arbeitserleichterung und zur Bewältigung gemeinsamer Herausforderungen identifiziert. Dies unterstreicht zugleich die Relevanz, in der weiteren Projektphase von openCost verstärkt am internen Kostenmanagement wissenschaftlicher Einrichtungen zu arbeiten. Schließlich befasste sich die Diskussion mit der Frage, wie Publikationen zuverlässig als vertragsfinanziert identifiziert werden können. Hierbei wurde die Elektronische Zeitschriftenbibliothek (EZB) als möglicher Referenzpunkt für einrichtungsindividuelle Vertragsinformationen hervorgehoben. Diskutiert wurde, welche bestehenden Systeme bereits genutzt werden, welche Synergien möglich sind und wie sich Schnittstellen – etwa zu LAS:eR, FOLIO oder über API-Abgleiche – künftig bestmöglich gestalten lassen. Auch die Erwartungen an eine künftige Vertrags-Registry wurden thematisiert, insbesondere in Hinblick auf Funktionen, Zugriffsebenen und die Integration in bestehende Workflows.</p>
</section>
<section id="transparenz" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="transparenz">Transparenz</h2>
<p>Die Station „Transparenz“ lud Teilnehmende dazu ein, über Maßnahmen zur Förderung von Kostentransparenz an ihren Einrichtungen zu sprechen. Teilnehmende betonten, dass es zunächst wichtig sei, den Adressatenkreis der Transparenzinitiative zu definieren: Für wen und zu welchem Zweck soll Transparenz geschaffen werden, und auf welcher Ebene? Daraus können Anforderungen an die Datengrundlage abgeleitet werden, etwa die Aggregationstiefe. In den Gesprächen stellte sich heraus, dass Transparenzbestrebungen an den Einrichtungen variieren. Ihr Erfolg ist häufig abhängig von der Ausgestaltung der Zusammenarbeit der beteiligten Einheiten, beispielsweise ob die datensammelnde Stelle Einsicht in das Finanzmanagementsystem erhält. Teilnehmende berichteten, dass Transparenz als Steuerungsmittel von Hochschulleitungen gewünscht ist. Die Erfahrung zeigt, dass ein Auftrag der Hochschulleitung Bibliotheken dabei hilft, dezentrale Kosten zu erfassen; er kann jedoch auch für Spannungen zwischen der Bibliothek und Fakultäten sorgen. Teilnehmende betonen, dass Transparenz nicht nur zur Kommunikation nach außen wichtig ist - Transparenz über die Aufteilung der Kosten innerhalb der Einrichtung ist ebenfalls wichtig. Mit Blick auf die Transparenz seitens der Verlage stellten die Teilnehmenden fest, dass sich einige Verlage bereits um Transparenz bemühen. Preise alleine seien jedoch schwer zu beurteilen, ohne auch die Produktionskosten zu kennen und einschätzen zu können, z.B. welche Ausgaben für Marketing angemessen sind. In Verhandlungen wäre ein vollständiger Überblick über die informationsbezogenen Finanzströme einer Einrichtung ideal, Non-Disclosure-Agreements stehen dem jedoch entgegen. Teilnehmende stellten fest, dass Non-Disclosure-Agreements vermieden werden können, wenn dies Teil des Mandats in Verhandlungen ist, wie ein Beispiel aus der Schweiz zeigt.</p>
</section>
<section id="offene-daten" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="offene-daten">Offene Daten</h2>
<p>Im Mittelpunkt der Diskussion an Station 3 stand die Nutzung offener Datenquellen für das Open-Access-Monitoring, insbesondere im Hinblick auf Publikationsaufkommen und -kosten. Die Teilnehmenden tauschten Erfahrungen, Herausforderungen und Perspektiven für die zukünftige Nutzung aus. Dabei zeigte sich, dass offene Daten bereits vielfältig eingesetzt werden, ihre Qualität und Verlässlichkeit jedoch stark variieren. Einige Teilnehmende berichteten, dass an ihren Einrichtungen offene Datenquellen genutzt werden – zum Beispiel OpenAlex für das Publikationsmonitoring. Die Erfahrungen zeigen, dass die Nutzung von OpenAlex einige Limitationen mit sich bringt. So variiert beispielsweise die Abdeckung der Disziplinen. OpenAlex erfasst außerdem eine Vielzahl an Publikationstypen, was zu einem „Overreporting“ führen kann. Eine weitere Herausforderung stellt die Datenqualität dar; etwa erschweren fehlende Affiliationsangaben eine effektive Nutzung. Teilnehmende betonten zudem, dass OpenAlex nur aktuelle Verlagslistenpreise abbildet, nicht jedoch die tatsächlich angefallenen Kosten. Der Dienst ist daher für das Kostenmonitoring nicht geeignet. Weitere genutzte offene Datenquellen sind unter anderem Unpaywall, Crossref, Sherpa/Romeo, DOAJ, Wikidata, DataCite und DBLP (insbesondere für die Informatik). Einige Einrichtungen ergänzen offene Daten durch Verlagsdashboards oder Verwaltungsdaten, um ein vollständigeres Bild zu erhalten. Über die Diskussion zum Thema Datenqualität hinaus wurde auch die Veränderlichkeit offener Datenquellen thematisiert: Angemerkt wurde, dass Aktualisierungen der Daten eine Herausforderung darstellen können. Betont wurde jedoch das Potenzial offener Daten. Sie, so die Teilnehmenden, können wesentlich zur Transparenz, Vergleichbarkeit und Effizienz in der Open-Access-Berichterstattung beitragen – vorausgesetzt, ihre Qualität, Pflege und Integration in institutionelle Infrastrukturen werden weiter verbessert. Damit offene Daten im Monitoring künftig eine tragende Rolle spielen können, nannten die Teilnehmenden mehrere Voraussetzungen: die Verbesserung der Datenqualität und Standardisierung, die Nachvollziehbarkeit von Änderungen und die Einführung einer Versionierung, die Verknüpfbarkeit mit institutionellen Datenquellen, transparente Governance-Strukturen für die Pflege und Weiterentwicklung der Daten sowie eine Community-basierte Qualitätssicherung und den Austausch zwischen Einrichtungen über Nutzungsperspektiven.</p>
</section>
<section id="fazit" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="fazit">Fazit</h2>
<p>Die Diskussionen an den drei Stationen verdeutlichten, dass die Komplexität von Open-Access-Modellen und Kostenstrukturen eine zentrale Herausforderung für das Monitoring darstellt. Zwar müssen organisatorische und technische Lösungen – wie die Etablierung geeigneter Workflows, die Zuweisung von Rollen oder die Anbindung von Schnittstellen – in jeder Einrichtung individuell umgesetzt werden. Zugleich wurde deutlich, dass alle Einrichtungen vor vergleichbaren Herausforderungen stehen, insbesondere im Bereich der Kostenerfassung. Daraus ergibt sich ein klarer Auftrag, gemeinsame Standards und Werkzeuge weiterzuentwickeln, die lokal angepasst werden können, aber dennoch einheitliche und vergleichbare Lösungen ermöglichen. Die Beiträge der Teilnehmenden zeigten auch, dass Zweck und Adressat*innen von Transparenzinitiativen definiert werden sollten, damit Maßnahmen zielgerichtet geplant werden können. Die Nutzung offener Datenquellen könnte durch Hilfestellungen zum Umgang mit Limitationen und zur Datenbereinigung gefördert werden. Für die drei Projekte OA Datenpraxis, openCost und Transform2Open wurden in dem sehr anregenden und informativen Workshop weitere Handlungsfelder für die weitere Arbeit identifiziert.</p>
<p>Hinweis: Dieser Post wird parallel bei <a href="https://www.opencost.de">openCost</a> veröffentlicht.</p>
<p>Weitere Informationen über die Forschungsgruppe Information Management an der Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin finden sich auf der <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">offiziellen Website</a> der Gruppe.</p>
<p>Dieser Text – mit Ausnahme von Zitaten und anderweitig gekennzeichneten Abschnitten – steht unter der <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
<div id="ref-pampel_praktiken_2025" class="csl-entry">
Pampel, Heinz, Lisa-Marie Stein, Bernhard Mittermaier, Dorothea Strecker, Bianca Schweighofer, and Gernot Deinzer. 2025. <span>“Praktiken Und <span>Infrastrukturen</span> Des <span>Open</span>-<span>Access</span>-<span>Monitorings</span>.”</span> Konstanz. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.17198826">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.17198826</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{pampel2025,
  author = {Pampel, Heinz and Stein, Lisa-Marie and Mittermaier,
    Bernhard and Strecker, Dorothea and Schweighofer, Bianca and
    Deinzer, Gernot},
  title = {Praktiken Und {Infrastrukturen} Des
    {Open-Access-Monitorings}},
  date = {2025-10-27},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/g6jdg-ejp06},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-pampel2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Pampel, Heinz, Lisa-Marie Stein, Bernhard Mittermaier, Dorothea
Strecker, Bianca Schweighofer, and Gernot Deinzer. 2025.
<span>“Praktiken Und Infrastrukturen Des
Open-Access-Monitorings.”</span> October 27, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/g6jdg-ejp06">https://doi.org/10.59350/g6jdg-ejp06</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-10-27-praktiken-und-infrastrukturen-des-open-access-monioring/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 26 Oct 2025 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-10-27-praktiken-und-infrastrukturen-des-open-access-monioring/oat.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="80" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Scholarly Blogs as an Integral Part of the Open Access Landscape</title>
  <dc:creator>Catharina Ochsner</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Björn Gebert</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Melanie Seltmann</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Ulrike Wuttke</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-10-07-scholarly-blogs-as-an-integral-part-of-the-open-access-landscape/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-10-07-scholarly-blogs-as-an-integral-part-of-the-open-access-landscape/OA25Workshop.jpeg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The Infra Wiss Blogs project by the Research Group Information Management was represented at this year’s <a href="https://open-access-tage.de/open-access-tage-2025-konstanz">Open Access Days</a> with the workshop “Scholarly blogs as an integral part of the open access landscape”. The workshop was organised by Catharina Ochsner and Heinz Pampel (<a href="https://www.hu-berlin.de/de">Humboldt Universität zu Berlin (HU Berlin)</a>, <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de">Berlin School of Library and Information Science (IBI)</a> in collaboration with Björn Gebert (<a href="https://mittelalter.hypotheses.org/">Mittelalterblog</a> &amp; <a href="https://www.sub.uni-goettingen.de/sub-aktuell/">Niedersächsische Staats-und Universitätsbibliothek Göttingen</a>), Melanie Seltmann (HU, IBI) and Ulrike Wuttke (<a href="https://www.fh-potsdam.de/">University of Applied Sciences Potsdam, SeDOA</a>).</p>
<p>Guided by the question “How can science blogs be institutionally anchored as an integral part of the open access landscape?” participants examined the opportunities and challenges of institutionally linking scholarly blogs. Initial results from the Infra Wiss Blogs project were presented <span class="citation" data-cites="ochsner2025">(Ochsner et al. 2025)</span>. The aim of the workshop was to develop an understanding of the role of blogs as sustainable open access infrastructures, identify institutional challenges and develop solutions for the institutional integration of scholarly blogs in order to promote science blogs in the spirit of open access in a sustainable manner. This blog post documents the workshop from the organisers’ perspective.</p>
<section id="discussion" class="level1">
<h1>Discussion</h1>
<p>Based on two thesis participants discussed the role of scholarly blogs as open access tools.</p>
<section id="thesis-1" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thesis-1">Thesis 1</h2>
<p><strong>Information infrastructure facilities must offer the possibility of archiving and persistent addressing of science blogs.</strong> On the one hand, participants emphasised that scholarly blogs are important for the visibility and accessibility of scientific content and should therefore be included in long-term archiving in a similar way to other forms of publication. On the other hand, participants pointed out that resources, responsibilities and technical standards still remain unclear. A recurring issue concerned the independence of bloggers. Many participants value the freedom to publish without institutional guidelines. Yet, it was also acknowledged that long-term archiving requires rules and processes. Scholarly blogs, described during the workshop as the “punk rock of publishing,” are spontaneous, independent, and unconventional—features not always compatible with formal requirements. Also, some bloggers wished to maintain a possibility to delete their posts in the future. As a possible solution, participants suggested plugins that make metadata easily reusable, among other things. Discussion also focused on which actors should be responsible for long-term availability: a mandatory deposit at the German National Library (DNB), state library repositories, consortia, or collaboratively maintained infrastructures. Federalism was identified as an obstacle in this context. Participants also opposed granting monopoly positions to single institutions, not least with regard to the researchers’ own academic journey from one institution to another, instead advocating for an independent infrastructure. Responsibility for the long-term availability of scholarly blogs was also assigned to scholarly blog platforms, in particular <a href="https://hypotheses.org/">Hypotheses</a>. According to the participants, these should develop an archiving strategy, also in cooperation with the German National Library (DNB). In contrast, those who host a blog themselves are responsible for its long-term availability, according to the participants.</p>
</section>
<section id="thesis-2" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thesis-2">Thesis 2</h2>
<p><strong>Scholarly bloggers are encouraged to ensure that they comply with open science practices and FAIR principles.</strong></p>
<p>According to the participants, there were also differing perspectives on this topic. On the one hand, it was acknowledged that bloggers should bear a minimum degree of personal responsibility. On the other hand, the participants agreed that individual researchers could not be expected to have comprehensive technical or information science knowledge. The participants emphasised that the motivation of many bloggers lies primarily in making their topic accessible and bringing it into scientific discourse – not in systematically pursuing open science. According to the participants, libraries and information infrastructures could play an important role here: they could transfer skills, create technical frameworks and facilitate compliance with standards. Participants critically discussed the applicability of the FAIR principles <span class="citation" data-cites="FAIR">(Wilkinson et al. 2016)</span>. Since the FAIR principles were originally developed for research data, they are not a “natural fit” for blogs and would need adaptation, according to statements made in the workshop. In addition, participants pointed out that not all bloggers want to make their content interoperable or reusable – especially with regard to its use by Artificial Intelligence (AI) processes. Instead of rigid requirements, it was therefore suggested that specific guidelines for blogs be developed, based, for example, on the principles of good scientific practice (GWP) that also names blogs as a publication medium <span class="citation" data-cites="GWP">(Forschungsgemeinschaft 2025)</span>. The contributions also made it clear that blanket demands carry the risk of reinforcing existing inequalities among bloggers. According to the participants, many scholars have neither the time nor the technical resources to comply with complex standards. It therefore remains important to respect the autonomy of bloggers while providing low-threshold support services.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level1">
<h1>Conclusion</h1>
<p>Scholarly blogs are already an important part of open science communication today: they create visibility, increase accessibility and enable a low-threshold form of scientific exchange. At the same time, numerous open questions arise with regard to institutional embedding, for example, questions about responsibilities, resources and technical standards.</p>
<p>Further information about the research group Information Management can be found on the <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official website</a> at Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labelled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
<div id="ref-GWP" class="csl-entry">
Forschungsgemeinschaft, Deutsche. 2025. <span>“Guidelines for <span>Safeguarding</span> <span>Good</span> <span>Research</span> <span>Practice</span>. <span>Code</span> of <span>Conduct</span>,”</span> January. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14281892">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14281892</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-ochsner2025" class="csl-entry">
Ochsner, Catharina, Heinz Pampel, Jonas Höfting, and Laura Rothfritz. 2025. <span>“Scholarly <span>Blogs</span>: <span>An</span> <span>Analysis</span> of <span>Infrastructural</span> <span>Aspects</span> <span>Based</span> on <span>German</span> <span>Scholarly</span> <span>Blogs</span>.”</span> <em>Journal of Documentation [In Press]</em>. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1108/JD-02-2025-0053">https://doi.org/10.1108/JD-02-2025-0053</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-FAIR" class="csl-entry">
Wilkinson, Mark D., Michel Dumontier, IJsbrand Jan Aalbersberg, Gabrielle Appleton, Myles Axton, Arie Baak, Niklas Blomberg, et al. 2016. <span>“The <span>FAIR</span> <span>Guiding</span> <span>Principles</span> for Scientific Data Management and Stewardship.”</span> <em>Scientific Data</em> 3 (1): 160018. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/sdata.2016.18">https://doi.org/10.1038/sdata.2016.18</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{ochsner2025,
  author = {Ochsner, Catharina and Pampel, Heinz and Gebert, Björn and
    Seltmann, Melanie and Wuttke, Ulrike},
  title = {Scholarly {Blogs} as an {Integral} {Part} of the {Open}
    {Access} {Landscape}},
  date = {2025-10-07},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/9fkvd-w2138},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-ochsner2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Ochsner, Catharina, Heinz Pampel, Björn Gebert, Melanie Seltmann, and
Ulrike Wuttke. 2025. <span>“Scholarly Blogs as an Integral Part of the
Open Access Landscape.”</span> October 7, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/9fkvd-w2138">https://doi.org/10.59350/9fkvd-w2138</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-10-07-scholarly-blogs-as-an-integral-part-of-the-open-access-landscape/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-10-07-scholarly-blogs-as-an-integral-part-of-the-open-access-landscape/OA25Workshop.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Report from the BUA fellowship: Metadata flows in the context of research data</title>
  <dc:creator>Dorothea Strecker</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-10-03-Report-from-the-BUA-fellowship-Metadata-flows-in-the-context-of-research-data/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>I recently returned from a research stay at the University of Ottawa: A grant by the Berlin University Alliance (BUA) - through the <a href="https://www.berlin-university-alliance.de/en/commitments/research-quality/forschung/fellowship/index.html">BUA Fellowship Program of the Objective 3 - Advancing Research Quality and Value</a> - allowed me to visit Stefanie Haustein, associate professor at the School of Information Studies at the University of Ottawa and co-director of the <a href="https://www.scholcommlab.ca/">Scholarly Communications Lab</a>.</p>
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-10-03-Report-from-the-BUA-fellowship-Metadata-flows-in-the-context-of-research-data/Desmarais_Building.jpeg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>During my stay, I investigated how metadata describing research data flows from local to global contexts. I previously wrote about my research and why it matters on this blog <span class="citation" data-cites="strecker_bua_2025">(Strecker 2025)</span>. In the course of my stay, I was able to collect and prepare data for analysis. As a first step, I reviewed records of the registry of research data repositories <a href="https://www.re3data.org">re3data</a> to check the status of OAI-PMH endpoints listed there. Next, I determined which endpoints expose metadata in specialized format using the <a href="https://rdamsc.bath.ac.uk">RDA Metadata Standards Catalog</a>, and checked which repositories have assigned DOIs to their resources. I selected 8 research data repositories - four from the social sciences and four from the geosciences. For each of these repositories, I retrieved metadata records based on (1) the specialized metadata schema, and (2) the DataCite Metadata Schema. The procedure I used ensures that these records describe the same resource, but in two different schemas. To prepare for the analysis, I updated and extended existing mappings between 3 specialized metadata schemas and the DataCite Metadata Schema. I am currently preparing a manuscript that will outline the results of this study.</p>
<p>In the six weeks I spent in Ottawa, I was also able to participate in another research activity - I contributed to a data collection initiative at the Scholarly Communications Lab that contextualized a recent suggestion by the National Institutes of Health (NIH) in the USA to cap APC funding. The data was initially used in a Science news article <span class="citation" data-cites="brainard_nih_nodate">(Brainard, n.d.)</span>. After extending the dataset further to include more journals and articles, it was published <span class="citation" data-cites="haustein_apcs_2025">(Haustein et al. 2025a)</span> alongside two blog posts <span class="citation" data-cites="haustein_nih_2025 the_scholarly_communications_lab_shaking_2025">(Haustein et al. 2025b; The Scholarly Communications Lab 2025)</span>.</p>
<p>I was also able to present my research to members of the Scholarly Communications Lab and University of Ottawa faculty members, and to discuss shared interests throughout my stay. Prof.&nbsp;Haustein also invited me to contribute materials on metadata for research data to a knowledge organization course.</p>
<p>The stay was very beneficial to my research. I was able to explore my chosen topic in depth and establish contact with colleagues that share my interests. I would like to thank the BUA for giving me this opportunity, and Stefanie Haustein, the Scholarly Communications Lab and University of Ottawa faculty for the welcoming atmosphere.</p>
<p>Further information about the research group can be found on our <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labelled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
<div id="ref-brainard_nih_nodate" class="csl-entry">
Brainard, Jeffrey. n.d. <span>“<span>NIH</span> Details Options for Limiting Its Payments for Open-Access Publishing Fees.”</span> <em>Science News</em>. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/science.zrf8mfm">https://doi.org/10.1126/science.zrf8mfm</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-haustein_apcs_2025" class="csl-entry">
Haustein, Stefanie, Eric Schares, Juan Pablo Alperin, Flavia Camargo, Lisa Matthias, Lucía Céspedes, Constance Poitras, and Dorothea Strecker. 2025a. <span>“<span>APCs</span> of 2,228 Journals Where <span>NIH</span>-Funded Authors Published in 2025.”</span> Harvard Dataverse. <a href="https://doi.org/10.7910/DVN/3XDMNF">https://doi.org/10.7910/DVN/3XDMNF</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-haustein_nih_2025" class="csl-entry">
———. 2025b. <span>“<span>NIH</span> Explores Capping <span>APCs</span>: <span>Let</span>’s Look at the Evidence.”</span> <em>Scholarly Communications Lab <span></span> ScholCommLab</em>. <a href="https://www.scholcommlab.ca/2025/09/03/nih-apc-caps/">https://www.scholcommlab.ca/2025/09/03/nih-apc-caps/</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-strecker_bua_2025" class="csl-entry">
Strecker, Dorothea. 2025. <span>“<span>BUA</span> Fellowship: <span>Metadata</span> Flows in the Context of Research Data.”</span> <em>Research Group Information Management @ Humboldt-Universität Zu Berlin</em>. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/wwwj7-4cm07">https://doi.org/10.59350/wwwj7-4cm07</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-the_scholarly_communications_lab_shaking_2025" class="csl-entry">
The Scholarly Communications Lab. 2025. <span>“Shaking up the Scholarly Publishing Market – <span>Why</span> Caps on <span>APCs</span> Could Backfire - <span>Impact</span> of <span>Social</span> <span>Sciences</span>.”</span> <em>LSE Impact Blog</em>. <a href="https://blogs.lse.ac.uk/impactofsocialsciences/2025/09/11/shaking-up-the-scholarly-publishing-market-why-caps-on-apcs-could-backfire/">https://blogs.lse.ac.uk/impactofsocialsciences/2025/09/11/shaking-up-the-scholarly-publishing-market-why-caps-on-apcs-could-backfire/</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{strecker2025,
  author = {Strecker, Dorothea},
  title = {Report from the {BUA} Fellowship: {Metadata} Flows in the
    Context of Research Data},
  date = {2025-10-03},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/fzz0a-wv919},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-strecker2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Strecker, Dorothea. 2025. <span>“Report from the BUA Fellowship:
Metadata Flows in the Context of Research Data.”</span> October 3, 2025.
<a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/fzz0a-wv919">https://doi.org/10.59350/fzz0a-wv919</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-10-03-Report-from-the-BUA-fellowship-Metadata-flows-in-the-context-of-research-data/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-10-03-Report-from-the-BUA-fellowship-Metadata-flows-in-the-context-of-research-data/Desmarais_Building.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Panel Discussion to Kick Off the International Open Access Week 2025</title>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-10-01-panel-discussion-to-kick-off-the-international-open-access-week/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>We are pleased to announce that the event series “Quo vadis Open Research in Berlin and Brandenburg” will continue throughout 2025 and 2026. This marks the fifth round of the series, bringing together experts and practitioners to discuss the future of Open Science in the Berlin-Brandenburg region.</p>
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-10-01-panel-discussion-to-kick-off-the-international-open-access-week/OAWeek2025.jpeg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>An overview of all events and participating organizations can be found on the <a href="https://open-access-brandenburg.de/quo-vadis-offene-wissenschaft-berlin-brandenburg-2025-2026/">official event website</a>.</p>
<p>The series will open with a kick-off event during the <a href="https://www.openaccessweek.org/">International Open Access Week 2025</a>.</p>
<p><strong>Date and time:</strong> October 20, 2025, 14:00–15:30 (CET)<br>
<strong>Theme:</strong> Open Access 2025: Collaborations for Open Publications<br>
<strong>Program and registration:</strong> <a href="https://open-access-brandenburg.de/events/open-access-2025-kooperationen-fuer-offene-publikationen-quo-vadis-2025/">open-access-brandenburg.de</a></p>
<p>Experts will discuss the current state and future perspectives of open access, focusing on how collaborations can strengthen open publishing practices. Please note: the event will take place in German.</p>
<p>The panel will include contributions from:</p>
<ul>
<li>Dr.&nbsp;Dagmar Meyer, European Research Council (ERC), Executive Agency (ERCEA)<br>
</li>
<li>Dr.&nbsp;Bernhard Mittermaier, Forschungszentrum Jülich, Central Library<br>
</li>
<li>Dr.&nbsp;Torsten Reimer, University of Chicago, Library</li>
</ul>
<p>The discussion is hosted by our research group at the Berlin School of Library and Information Science, Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin.</p>
<p>Another contribution from our group to Open Access Week 2025 is the co-organization of the conference “Berlin – City of Open Knowledge for Academia, Administration, Civil Society &amp; Culture.” The conference will take place on October 23, 2025. For more details, please see the <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/j9987-g2h67">announcement in this blog</a>.</p>
<p>Further information about our work can be found on our <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labeled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{pampel2025,
  author = {Pampel, Heinz},
  title = {Panel {Discussion} to {Kick} {Off} the {International} {Open}
    {Access} {Week} 2025},
  date = {2025-10-01},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/0mm4x-sma37},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-pampel2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Pampel, Heinz. 2025. <span>“Panel Discussion to Kick Off the
International Open Access Week 2025.”</span> October 1, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/0mm4x-sma37">https://doi.org/10.59350/0mm4x-sma37</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-10-01-panel-discussion-to-kick-off-the-international-open-access-week/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-10-01-panel-discussion-to-kick-off-the-international-open-access-week/OAWeek2025.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Berlin – City of Open Knowledge for Academia, Administration, Civil Society &amp; Culture</title>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-08-22-berlin-city-of-open-knowledge-for-academia-administration-civil-society-culture/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>I am pleased to share that our <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">research group</a> is a partner of the <a href="https://www.berlin-university-alliance.de/commitments/research-quality/openx/berlin-stow/index.html">“Berlin – City of Open Knowledge for Academia, Administration, Civil Society &amp; Culture”</a> conference.</p>
<p>The conference will take place on October 23, 2025, from 9:30 AM to 4:30 PM, as part of the international <a href="https://www.openaccessweek.org/">Open Access Week 2025</a>.</p>
<p>This event will bring together experts, practitioners, and engaged citizens to explore the future of open knowledge-sharing in Berlin. Through a variety of interactive formats, participants will discuss strategies, present projects, and identify opportunities for cross-sector collaboration. A key element of the program is an Open Lab / Barcamp session, designed for self-organized discussions, project showcases, and idea exchanges.</p>
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-08-22-berlin-city-of-open-knowledge-for-academia-administration-civil-society-culture/berlin_stadt_des_offenen_wissens.jpeg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Registration is <a href="https://www.berlin-university-alliance.de/commitments/research-quality/openx/berlin-stow/index.html">now open</a>. Please note, the conference will be held in German. The event will be hosted at the Seminarzentrum (Silberlaube) at Freie Universität Berlin.</p>
<p>The conference, supported by the Berlin University Alliance (BUA), is organized by colleagues from BUA, Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin, Open Research Office Berlin, Stiftung Preußischer Kulturbesitz, Staatsbibliothek zu Berlin, Universität der Künste, and Weizenbaum Institut.</p>
<p>Further information about the research group can be found on our <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labelled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{pampel2025,
  author = {Pampel, Heinz},
  title = {Berlin – {City} of {Open} {Knowledge} for {Academia,}
    {Administration,} {Civil} {Society} \&amp; {Culture}},
  date = {2025-08-22},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/j9987-g2h67},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-pampel2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Pampel, Heinz. 2025. <span>“Berlin – City of Open Knowledge for
Academia, Administration, Civil Society &amp; Culture.”</span> August
22, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/j9987-g2h67">https://doi.org/10.59350/j9987-g2h67</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-08-22-berlin-city-of-open-knowledge-for-academia-administration-civil-society-culture/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-08-22-berlin-city-of-open-knowledge-for-academia-administration-civil-society-culture/berlin_stadt_des_offenen_wissens.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Interview on Deutschlandfunk Kultur About Belgian Ruling Against Shadow Libraries</title>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-08-13-interview-on-deutschlandfunk-kultur/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Last week, I was interviewed on the program <a href="https://www.deutschlandfunkkultur.de/tracking-am-handgelenk-was-passiert-mit-den-daten-aus-unseren-wearables-100.html">Breitband</a> on Deutschlandfunk Kultur about the ruling of a Belgian court against four shadow libraries, as well as the Open Library of the Internet Archive (Krempl, 2025). The broadcast is now available <a href="https://www.deutschlandfunkkultur.de/tracking-am-handgelenk-was-passiert-mit-den-daten-aus-unseren-wearables-100.html">online</a>. Enjoy listening!</p>
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-08-13-interview-on-deutschlandfunk-kultur/interview-on-deutschlandfunk-kultur.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Further information about the research group can be found on our <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labelled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
<div id="ref-deutschlandfunkkulturde_fitness_2025" class="csl-entry">
deutschlandfunkkultur.de. 2025. <span>“Fitness <span>Tracker</span> Und <span>Co</span>: <span>Was</span> Passiert Mit Unseren Sensiblen <span>Daten</span>?”</span> <em>Deutschlandfunk Kultur</em>. <a href="https://www.deutschlandfunkkultur.de/tracking-am-handgelenk-was-passiert-mit-den-daten-aus-unseren-wearables-100.html">https://www.deutschlandfunkkultur.de/tracking-am-handgelenk-was-passiert-mit-den-daten-aus-unseren-wearables-100.html</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{pampel2025,
  author = {Pampel, Heinz},
  title = {Interview on {Deutschlandfunk} {Kultur} {About} {Belgian}
    {Ruling} {Against} {Shadow} {Libraries}},
  date = {2025-08-13},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/bn0bz-73473},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-pampel2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Pampel, Heinz. 2025. <span>“Interview on Deutschlandfunk Kultur About
Belgian Ruling Against Shadow Libraries.”</span> August 13, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/bn0bz-73473">https://doi.org/10.59350/bn0bz-73473</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-08-13-interview-on-deutschlandfunk-kultur/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-08-13-interview-on-deutschlandfunk-kultur/interview-on-deutschlandfunk-kultur.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>“Vom Drittmittelprojekt zur etablierten Struktur”. Bericht über ein Hands-on Lab auf der 113. Bibliocon</title>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Ursula Arning</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Brigitte Grote</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Gesche Wahlen</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Gerald Jagusch</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Martin Spenger</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Jürgen Rohrwild</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Robert Strötgen</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Christopher O. Khamis</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-08-08-bericht-ueber-ein-hands-on-lab-auf-der-113-bibliocon/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Wie wird aus einem geförderten Pilotprojekt eine dauerhaft tragfähige Infrastruktur? Diese zentrale Frage stellten sich viele der Teilnehmenden des Hands-on-Labs „Vom Drittmittelprojekt über die Community zur etablierten Struktur – Erfahrungsaustausch und Erarbeitung von Empfehlungen“ <span class="citation" data-cites="arning_vom_2025">(Arning et al. 2025)</span> auf dem 9. Bibliothekskongress / der 113. Bibliocon in Bremen am 26.06.2025.</p>
<p>Unser Hands-on-Labs bot einen Rahmen für Austausch, Vernetzung und gemeinsame Reflexion mit dem Ziel, praktische Empfehlungen für die Verstetigung von Informationsinfrastrukturen zu entwickeln.</p>
<p>Ein gemeinsamer Bezugspunkt aller beteiligten Infrastrukturen ist ihre Förderung im Rahmen des Programms <a href="https://www.dfg.de/de/foerderung/foerdermoeglichkeiten/programme/infrastruktur/lis/lis-foerderangebote/vigo">„Verantwortung für Informationsinfrastrukturen gemeinsam organisieren“ (VIGO)</a> der Deutschen Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG). Dieses Programm wurde von der DFG eingerichtet, um dem weit verbreiteten Problem der mangelnden Verstetigung von Projektergebnissen entgegenzuwirken. Allzu oft bleiben Softwarelösungen und Services nach dem Ende der Projektförderung ohne institutionelle Anbindung und verschwinden – trotz intensiver Entwicklungsarbeit – aus der Community. Die Förderung im Rahmen des VIGO-Formats unterstützt gezielt solche Projekte, die nachhaltige Strukturen aufbauen wollen: mit einem Fokus auf Community-Beteiligung, organisatorische Verstetigung und langfristige Finanzierungsmodelle. Seit 2024 sind fünf Projekte aus dem Programm gestartet (<a href="https://www.kitodo.org">Kitodo e.V.</a>, <a href="https://rdmorganiser.github.io">RDMO e.V.</a>, das <a href="https://www.open-encyclopedia-system.org">Open Encyclopedia System</a>, <a href="https://infrawissblogs.org/">Infra Wiss Blogs</a> sowie <a href="https://www.zbmed.de/forschen/laufende-projekte/wau">WAU – Wissensmanagement AG Universitätsverlage</a>, deren Vertreter:innen das Hands-on-Lab mitgestaltet haben.</p>
<p>Nach einer kurzen Einführung in Ziel und Ablauf der Veranstaltung teilten Vertreter:innen dieser Communities ihre Erfahrungen und Ziele in prägnanten Impulsbeiträgen. Dabei wurden neben erfolgreichen Maßnahmen auch die Herausforderungen benannt, die sich beim Aufbau tragfähiger Strukturen ergeben, etwa bei der Wahl der Rechtsform, der Finanzierung oder der Aktivierung der Community.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.kitodo.org/">Key to digital objects - Kitodo e.V.</a> Mission: Nachhaltige Weiterentwicklung der Digitalisierungssoftware Kitodo Maßnahmen: Vereinsgründung 2012, DFG-Großprojekt, Aufbau eines Entwicklungsfonds<br>
Herausforderungen: Komplexität heterogener Open-Source-Communities vs.&nbsp;einfache Dienstleisterlösungen</p>
<p><a href="https://rdmorganiser.github.io/">RDMO.Research Data Management Organiser e.V.</a> Mission: Releasemanagement, Unterstützung von Entwickler:innen und Community<br>
Maßnahmen: Vereinsgründung 2024, 21 Mitglieder, Satzung verabschiedet<br>
Herausforderungen: Gemeinnützigkeit, Governance, Mitgliedschaftsmodelle</p>
<p><a href="https://www.open-encyclopedia-system.org/">Open Encyclopedia System (ComOES)</a> Mission: Aufbau tragfähiger Strukturen für Zusammenarbeit und Austausch<br>
Maßnahmen: Anforderungsanalyse, Community-Workshops, Informationsangebote<br>
Herausforderungen: Aktivierung der Community, Anreize schaffen, Dezentralisierung</p>
<p><a href="https://infrawissblogs.org/">Infra Wiss Blogs</a> Mission: Sicherung der langfristigen Zugänglichkeit wissenschaftlicher Blogs<br>
Maßnahmen: Analyse, Community-Aufbau, Lösungsentwicklung<br>
Herausforderungen: Individualität des Bloggens vs.&nbsp;institutionelle Infrastruktur</p>
<p><a href="https://www.zbmed.de/forschen/laufende-projekte/wau">WAU – Wissensmanagement AG Universitätsverlage</a> Mission: Nachhaltiger Austausch, Standardisierung, Sichtbarkeit für Library Publishing<br>
Maßnahmen: Vergleich von Workflows, Aufbau eines Living Handbooks als Wissensbasis auch außerhalb der AG Universitätsverlage<br>
Herausforderungen: Disziplinenvielfalt, heterogene Strukturen</p>
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-08-08-bericht-ueber-ein-hands-on-lab-auf-der-113-bibliocon/hands_on_lab_vigo_1.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<section id="leitfragen" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="leitfragen">Leitfragen</h2>
<p>Im Zentrum des Hands-on-Labs stand eine intensive Gruppenarbeitsphase in Form eines World Cafés. Alle Teilnehmenden durchliefen drei moderierte Stationen, an denen konkrete Fragestellungen zur Verstetigung von Projekten diskutiert wurden. Die Ergebnisse wurden anschließend im Plenum zusammengetragen und werden im Folgenden dokumentiert.</p>
<section id="wie-gewinnt-man-interessierte-anwendende-und-baut-eine-aktive-community-auf" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="wie-gewinnt-man-interessierte-anwendende-und-baut-eine-aktive-community-auf">1. Wie gewinnt man interessierte Anwendende und baut eine aktive Community auf?</h3>
<p>Ein zentrales Ergebnis der Diskussion war: Erfolgreiches Community-Building beginnt nicht erst nach dem Projektabschluss, sondern idealerweise bereits in der frühen Konzeptionsphase. Projekte sollten von Beginn an transparent kommunizieren, wer mitwirken kann, und möglichst niedrigschwellige Beteiligungsangebote schaffen. Kommunikation auf Augenhöhe und das ernsthafte Einbinden von Nutzer:innen in Entscheidungen, etwa durch Testphasen, offene Roadmaps oder partizipative Gremien, fördern die Identifikation mit dem Projekt. Als besonders wirkungsvoll wurden persönliche Kontakte, gezielte Ansprache über bestehende Netzwerke und die Nutzung von Testimonials genannt. Wichtig sei es, den konkreten Mehrwert für potenzielle Mitstreitende klar aufzuzeigen, z.B. durch Mitgestaltungsmöglichkeiten oder durch Hinweise darauf, was bei einem Scheitern der Infrastruktur verloren ginge.</p>
</section>
<section id="welche-werkzeuge-und-maßnahmen-unterstützen-den-aufbau-einer-stabilen-community" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="welche-werkzeuge-und-maßnahmen-unterstützen-den-aufbau-einer-stabilen-community">2. Welche Werkzeuge und Maßnahmen unterstützen den Aufbau einer stabilen Community?</h3>
<p>Mit dieser Leitfrage wurden organisatorische und technische Instrumente zur Stärkung der Community adressiert. Genannt wurden u.a. kollaborative Plattformen für Dokumentation und Austausch (z. B. Wikis, Mailinglisten, GitHub), regelmäßige Online- und Präsenztreffen sowie modulare Governance-Modelle mit klar verteilten Rollen. Insbesondere Open-Source-Modelle wurden als förderlich für Transparenz und Mitwirkung angesehen – vorausgesetzt, es existiert eine koordinierende Stelle, die Beiträge moderiert und Entwicklungen konsolidiert. Die Diskussion zeigte auch, dass eine professionelle Projektkoordination entscheidend ist: Nur wenn Aufgaben wie Kommunikation, Dokumentation oder Support verlässlich übernommen werden, entsteht Vertrauen in die Verlässlichkeit der Infrastruktur. Communities benötigen Ansprechpersonen, die die Interaktion fördern, Feedback aufgreifen und Impulse für Weiterentwicklungen setzen.</p>
</section>
<section id="was-sind-geeignete-organisations--und-rechtsformen-für-nachhaltige-strukturen" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="was-sind-geeignete-organisations--und-rechtsformen-für-nachhaltige-strukturen">3. Was sind geeignete Organisations- und Rechtsformen für nachhaltige Strukturen?</h3>
<p>Auch die Frage nach passenden organisatorischen Rahmenbedingungen wurde diskutiert. Viele Projekte befinden sich im Übergang von informellen Strukturen zu formalen Organisationen – etwa in Form eingetragener Vereine. Die Diskussion machte deutlich: Eine Gemeinnützigkeit ist zwar wünschenswert (z. B. zur Mittelakquise), aber mit hohem bürokratischen Aufwand verbunden und oft schwer zu erreichen. Mitgliedsbeiträge allein decken die Betriebskosten in der Regel nicht; vielmehr setzen viele Communities auf Mischfinanzierungen – etwa durch die Einbindung von Ressourcen aus Trägereinrichtungen oder durch Kooperationsmodelle. Als vorteilhaft wurden konsortiale Strukturen und kooperative Netzwerke benannt, in denen Aufgaben arbeitsteilig verteilt und Ressourcen gemeinsam getragen werden. Dabei sei es zentral, Governance-Strukturen nicht nur effizient, sondern auch sichtbar und nachvollziehbar zu gestalten – z. B. durch Vorstände, Beiräte oder öffentliche Geschäftsordnungen. Gleichzeitig wurde betont, dass auch schlanke, projektnahe Strukturen funktionieren können, solange alle gemeinsam daran arbeiten, sich engagieren und organisatorische Aufgaben reihum übernehmen.</p>
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-08-08-bericht-ueber-ein-hands-on-lab-auf-der-113-bibliocon/hands_on_lab_vigo_2.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="perspektiven-und-nächste-schritte" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="perspektiven-und-nächste-schritte">Perspektiven und nächste Schritte</h2>
<p>Die Diskussionen zeigten, dass der Weg von der Projektförderung hin zu einer verstetigten Infrastruktur kein Automatismus, sondern ein aktiver, oft herausfordernder Gestaltungsprozess ist. Erfolgsfaktoren sind frühzeitige Beteiligung, klare Verantwortlichkeiten, transparente Kommunikationswege und tragfähige Organisationsformen. Besonders betont wurde die Bedeutung gemeinsamer Werte wie Offenheit, Teilhabe und Verlässlichkeit, aber auch das Spannungsfeld zwischen Idealismus und Pragmatismus. Das Hands-on-Lab verstand sich als Auftakt für einen kontinuierlichen Austausch zum Thema.</p>
<p>Weitere Informationen über die Forschungsgruppe Information Management an der Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin finden sich auf der [offiziellen Website] der Gruppe. (http://hu.berlin/infomgnt).</p>
<p>Dieser Text – mit Ausnahme von Zitaten und anderweitig gekennzeichneten Abschnitten – steht unter der <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 Lizenz</a>.</p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
<div id="ref-arning_vom_2025" class="csl-entry">
Arning, Ursula, Brigitte Grote, Gerald Jagusch, Heinz Pampel, Jürgen Rohrwild, Martin Spenger, Robert Strötgen, and Gesche Wahlen. 2025. <span>“Vom <span>Drittmittelprojekt</span> Über Die <span>Community</span> Zur Etablierten <span>Struktur</span> – <span>Erfahrungsaustausch</span> Und <span>Erarbeitung</span> von <span>Empfehlungen</span>.”</span> In. Bremen. <a href="https://nbn-resolving.org/urn:nbn:de:0290-opus4-194638">https://nbn-resolving.org/urn:nbn:de:0290-opus4-194638</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{pampel2025,
  author = {Pampel, Heinz and Arning, Ursula and Grote, Brigitte and
    Wahlen, Gesche and Jagusch, Gerald and Spenger, Martin and Rohrwild,
    Jürgen and Strötgen, Robert and O. Khamis, Christopher},
  title = {“{Vom} {Drittmittelprojekt} Zur Etablierten {Struktur}”.
    {Bericht} Über Ein {Hands-on} {Lab} Auf Der 113. {Bibliocon}},
  date = {2025-08-08},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/b1n5j-rz617},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-pampel2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Pampel, Heinz, Ursula Arning, Brigitte Grote, Gesche Wahlen, Gerald
Jagusch, Martin Spenger, Jürgen Rohrwild, Robert Strötgen, and
Christopher O. Khamis. 2025. <span>“<span>‘Vom Drittmittelprojekt Zur
Etablierten Struktur.’</span> Bericht Über Ein Hands-on Lab Auf Der 113.
Bibliocon.”</span> August 8, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/b1n5j-rz617">https://doi.org/10.59350/b1n5j-rz617</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-08-08-bericht-ueber-ein-hands-on-lab-auf-der-113-bibliocon/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-08-08-bericht-ueber-ein-hands-on-lab-auf-der-113-bibliocon/hands_on_lab_vigo_2.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Long Night of Science 2025: Communicating Information Management with a Data Puzzle on Open Science</title>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Friedrich Schmidgall</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Laura Rothfritz</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Max Liebel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Johanna Schielke</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-31-Long-Night-of-Science-2025-Communicating-Information-Management-with-a-Data-Puzzle-on-Open-Science/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>The <a href="https://www.langenachtderwissenschaften.de">Long Night of Science (Lange Nacht der Wissenschaften - LNdW)</a> is one of the most well-known public science events in Germany, providing research institutions with a platform for science communication. During this annual event, researchers present their work to an interested and engaged public.</p>
<p>Our research group at the <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de">Berlin School of Library and Information Science (IBI)</a> at Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin participated in the Berlin event for the first time this year, joining the celebration of LNdW’s 25th anniversary <span class="citation" data-cites="pampel_wissenschaftliche_2025">(Pampel et al. 2025)</span>.</p>
<p>Through our affiliation with the <a href="https://www.digital-future.berlin">Einstein Center Digital Future (ECDF)</a>, we had the opportunity to collaborate with Friedrich Schmidgall, head of the ECDF Micro Factory, to develop a hands-on exhibit showcasing our research in the field of information management.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://www.digital-future.berlin/haus-der-digitalisierung/micro-factory/">ECDF Micro Factory</a> provides ECDF researchers with space and experimental formats to explore ideas and create solutions outside of traditional academic structures. It offers both conceptual and technical support for the development of tangible and digital objects, using prototyping methods ranging from paper and cardboard to mockups and 3D-printed materials.</p>
<p>Our goal was to convey key concepts of Information Management and Open Science practices in a playful and accessible way. In our initial discussions with Friedrich Schmidgall, we came up with the idea of an animated “data puzzle” titled Information Management for Open Science, designed to illustrate two central themes of our research.</p>
<p>Friedrich Schmidgall then transformed our idea into an interactive exhibit in the form of a physical puzzle and a projected animation.</p>
<p>The installation featured a tabletop puzzle illuminated by an overhead projector. At first glance, visitors saw only projected outlines on the table surface, indicating empty spaces for the puzzle pieces, each marked with a unique icon representing a specific subject of the “data puzzle”. The interactive experience invited participants to find physical puzzle pieces with matching icons and place them in their designated spaces. With each correct placement, a new segment of the larger “data puzzle” emerged, revealing subject-specific information and QR codes that linked to an identifier online. As the puzzle took shape piece by piece, the complete visualization gradually emerged, guiding visitors through concepts of information management with both visual and tactile exploration.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-31-Long-Night-of-Science-2025-Communicating-Information-Management-with-a-Data-Puzzle-on-Open-Science/data-puzzle-lndw-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption"><em>Visitors and team members in conversation at the puzzle installation (Credit: ECDF/PR/allefarben-foto)</em></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>To enable this interaction, we fitted the nine laser-cut acrylic puzzle pieces with uniquely positioned magnets. These magnets interacted with Hall effect sensors embedded in the tabletop surface. Only correctly placed puzzle pieces aligned their magnet with a sensor, thus triggering the projection of the corresponding segment of the “data puzzle”. The sensors were connected to an <a href="https://www.arduino.cc/">Arduino microcontroller</a> running <a href="https://github.com/firmata/arduino">Firmata</a>, communicating sensor data to a host computer through serial connection. Processing of the sensor data and projection control were handled by the programmable multimedia toolkit <a href="https://vvvv.org/">vvvv beta</a>. The vvvv patch also included a GUI that allowed fine-tuning of the projection’s position and scale, ensuring proper alignment even if the projector was not mounted perfectly.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-31-Long-Night-of-Science-2025-Communicating-Information-Management-with-a-Data-Puzzle-on-Open-Science/data-puzzle-lndw-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption"><em>Model of the puzzle (Credit: ECDF/Friedrich Schmidgall)</em></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>We tested the <a href="https://www.langenachtderwissenschaften.de/programm/detail/51432">object</a> in various research contexts. In the first version, we used an abstract example unrelated to a specific research project. During the trials, we found that explaining the interplay between people, projects, research data, infrastructures, and other resources of scholarly work often required concrete, real-world examples. In response, our second prototype used developments in CRISPR gene editing as a case study, which, while more engaging, highlighted specific challenges in communicating aspects of Open Science in the life sciences.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-31-Long-Night-of-Science-2025-Communicating-Information-Management-with-a-Data-Puzzle-on-Open-Science/data-puzzle-lndw-3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption"><em>Model of the puzzle (Credit: ECDF/Friedrich Schmidgall)</em></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>We ultimately selected the <a href="https://mosaic-expedition.org/">MOSAiC expedition</a> as the central example for our installation, the largest Arctic research expedition in history. Its relevance to climate research and the use of a large-scale research infrastructure, namely, research vessel Polarstern, offered an ideal context for conveying fundamental concepts of Information Management.</p>
<p>The interactive “data puzzle” was first presented to the public at the opening of the Long Night of Science on July 13, 2025.</p>
<p>The photos in this blog post provide a few glimpses of the exhibit in action. We were thrilled by the remarkable interest it generated. Until close to midnight, we presented our work in rotating shifts. Since the object was not entirely self-explanatory, it sparked many engaging conversations that also gave us an opportunity to reflect on our own research.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-31-Long-Night-of-Science-2025-Communicating-Information-Management-with-a-Data-Puzzle-on-Open-Science/data-puzzle-lndw-4jpg.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption"><em>Visitors and team members in conversation at the puzzle installation (Credit: ECDF/PR/allefarben-foto)</em></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Further information about the research group can be found on our <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labelled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
<div id="ref-pampel_wissenschaftliche_2025" class="csl-entry">
Pampel, Heinz, Friedrich Schmidgall, Laura Rothfritz, Max Liebel, and Johanna Schielke. 2025. <span>“Wissenschaftliche <span>Ergebnisse</span> Offen Zugänglich Machen Durch <span>Information</span> <span>Management</span>. <span>Forschungspuzzle</span>.”</span> In. Berlin. <a href="https://www.langenachtderwissenschaften.de/programm/detail/51432">https://www.langenachtderwissenschaften.de/programm/detail/51432</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{pampel2025,
  author = {Pampel, Heinz and Schmidgall, Friedrich and Rothfritz, Laura
    and Liebel, Max and Schielke, Johanna},
  title = {Long {Night} of {Science} 2025: {Communicating} {Information}
    {Management} with a {Data} {Puzzle} on {Open} {Science}},
  date = {2025-07-31},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/bd65p-7r071},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-pampel2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Pampel, Heinz, Friedrich Schmidgall, Laura Rothfritz, Max Liebel, and
Johanna Schielke. 2025. <span>“Long Night of Science 2025: Communicating
Information Management with a Data Puzzle on Open Science.”</span> July
31, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/bd65p-7r071">https://doi.org/10.59350/bd65p-7r071</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-31-Long-Night-of-Science-2025-Communicating-Information-Management-with-a-Data-Puzzle-on-Open-Science/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-31-Long-Night-of-Science-2025-Communicating-Information-Management-with-a-Data-Puzzle-on-Open-Science/data-puzzle-lndw-1.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Guide Published: Interplay of Institutional Repositories and CRIS</title>
  <dc:creator>Lisa Matthias</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Christopher Onzie Khamis</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-24-Guide-Published-Interplay-of-Institutional-Repositories-and-CRIS/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>To support repository managers and institutional decision-makers, we are pleased to present our second guide from the BMFTR-funded (Federal Ministry for Research, Technology and Space) project “Professionalisierung der Open-Access-Repositorien-Infrastruktur in Deutschland (Pro OAR DE)”: “Forschungsinformationssysteme (CRIS): Handlungsfeld für institutionelle Open-Access-Repositorien” (German only.)</p>
<p>Matthias, L., Pampel, H., Khamis, C. O., Rothfritz, L., &amp; Wrzesinski, M. (2025). <em>Forschungsinformationssysteme (CRIS): Handlungsfeld für institutionelle Open-Access-Repositorien. Pro OAR DE Handreichung.</em> Zenodo. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15800262" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15800262</a></p>
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-24-Guide-Published-Interplay-of-Institutional-Repositories-and-CRIS/FIS_Handreichung_Blogpost.jpeg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>This publication documents the outcomes of our December 11, 2024 <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/infomanagement/events/prooarde-cris">networking forum</a> on Current Research Information Systems (CRIS) and institutional repositories that brought together 67 Open Access professionals from across Germany. The resulting guide synthesizes the collective expertise and insights generated during this collaborative event, offering practical recommendations to enhance collaboration between institutional repositories and current research information systems.</p>
<p>Following expert presentations by <a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4905-1936">Daniel Beucke</a> (Göttingen State and University Library) and <a href="https://orcid.org/0009-0004-2098-8076">Malte Kramer</a> (CRIS.NRW), participants engaged in open discussions through a world café format, where they shared institutional experiences and developed practical approaches to common obstacles. The presentation slides from the expert talks are available <a href="https://zenodo.org/doi/10.5281/zenodo.14440151">online</a>.</p>
<p>The guide distills these rich discussions into actionable recommendations across six critical areas for repository managers:</p>
<section id="interoperability-for-automated-data-flows" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="interoperability-for-automated-data-flows">1. Interoperability for Automated Data Flows</h3>
<p>The participants identified essential prerequisites for successful interoperability. They emphasized that interoperability can only be guaranteed when the precise purposes of each actor and system are clearly defined as these purposes determine the required quality level, actual workload, and access authorizations for different data views (for researchers versus administrators) with appropriate granularity. This specificity is particularly important because interoperability exists in varying degrees, and the mapping of relationships must function bidirectionally between systems. Core challenges emerged around the standardization of metadata schemas, international connectivity through multilingual labels, and the consistent use of PIDs, particularly in the versioning of preprints. Attendees proposed several possible solutions. These included stakeholder involvement in determining responsibilities, clear guidance systems for data types, Linked Open Data, and regular quality management. Active participation in relevant networks and collaborative projects can further support these efforts.</p>
</section>
<section id="repository-and-cris---complementary-systems" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="repository-and-cris---complementary-systems">2. Repository and CRIS - Complementary Systems</h3>
<p>Critical organizational factors include the need for clear system definitions, the determination of a lead system, and the explicit institutional anchoring of responsibilities. Technical hurdles stem from diverse resource types and varying levels of metadata detail. The proposed solution begins with a comprehensive inventory analysis, followed by transparent assignment of responsibilities across departmental boundaries. The graphical representation of workflows was emphasized as a particularly valuable tool for communication among involved actors.</p>
</section>
<section id="standards-for-research-information" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="standards-for-research-information">3. Standards for Research Information</h3>
<p>Insufficient harmonization between the <a href="https://www.kerndatensatz-forschung.de/">KDSF – Standard für Forschungsinformationen in Deutschland</a> and library standards presents a significant obstacle, alongside further development of research evaluation criteria in the context of the <a href="https://coara.eu/">Coalition for Advancing Research Assessment (CoARA)</a> agreement. Participants identified consistent use of PIDs as a crucial technical prerequisite. CRIS systems show particular promise in adding value to the information budget through the systematic capture of publication costs.</p>
</section>
<section id="system-diversity-and-isolated-solutions" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="system-diversity-and-isolated-solutions">4. System Diversity and Isolated Solutions</h3>
<p>Participants identified several barriers, such as insufficient user-friendliness, imprecise requirement profiles, inadequate data management, and limited system upgradeability. To address these challenges, they proposed establishing institutional networking and cooperation strategies guided by a dedicated steering group. In addition, they highlighted the precise definition of responsibilities and the strategic involvement of the institutional leadership. Resources emerged as a crucial factor, with particular emphasis on securing adequate IT competencies. This should be complemented by professional project management. The group proposed that user requirements should be systematically documented through user stories and discussed in an interdisciplinary manner.</p>
</section>
<section id="diversity-of-data---publication-data-and-other-research-information" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="diversity-of-data---publication-data-and-other-research-information">5. Diversity of Data - Publication Data and Other Research Information</h3>
<p>At the organizational level, participants pointed to insufficient coordination as a central problem. This manifests in poor interdepartmental coordination, unclear responsibilities, and difficulties in collaboration. The situation is further complicated by the diversity of interest groups, different disciplinary cultures, and a lack of technical standards. To address these issues, participants recommended implementing a clear leadership strategy that meaningfully involves all stakeholders while precisely defining responsibilities. They placed particular emphasis on establishing ongoing dialogue with researchers, whose relief and support should be a central priority. The CoARA recommendations provide a valuable guiding framework for these efforts. From a technical perspective, participants advocated leveraging existing data sources like <a href="https://openalex.org/">OpenAlex</a> and adopting uniform data standards to enhance system interoperability.</p>
</section>
<section id="further-challenges" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="further-challenges">6. Further Challenges</h3>
<p>Organizationally, complexities arise in coordinating repositories and CRIS systems, requiring close collaboration among different organizational units. Technical considerations demand preserving the autonomy of individual systems while simultaneously developing uniform standards for various entry types. The disciplinary dimension adds another layer of complexity, requiring careful consideration of different institutional workflows. Attendees recommended an approach combining several key elements, such as a thoroughly documented, professionally moderated development process, sustainable financing models that ensure long-term viability, and targeted training initiatives at the intersection of administrative and technical requirements.</p>
<p>This guide provides a foundation for continued professional exchange. Repository operators, libraries, and institutional decision-makers will find valuable insights for dataflows between institutional Open Access repositories and CRIS systems.</p>
<p>We extend our sincere thanks to all forum participants who contributed their expertise and experience to this collaborative effort. We welcome your feedback and look forward to continuing this important dialogue as we collectively strengthen the Open Access repository landscape.</p>
<p>For more information about Pro OAR DE and our upcoming activities, please visit our <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/infomanagement/projekte/pro-oar-de">website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labeled sections – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.en">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
<div id="ref-matthias_forschungsinformationssysteme_2025" class="csl-entry">
Matthias, Lisa, Heinz Pampel, Christopher Onzie Khamis, Laura Rothfritz, and Marcel Wrzesinski. 2025. <span>“Forschungsinformationssysteme (<span>CRIS</span>): <span>Handlungsfeld</span> Für Institutionelle <span>Open</span>-<span>Access</span>-<span>Repositorien</span>. <span>Pro</span> <span>OAR</span> <span>DE</span> <span>Handreichung</span>.”</span> Zenodo. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15800262">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15800262</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-wrzesinski_pro_2024" class="csl-entry">
Wrzesinski, Marcel, Daniel Beucke, and Malte Kramer. 2024. <span>“Pro <span>OAR</span> <span>DE</span> <span>Vernetzungsforum</span>: <span>Institutionelle</span> <span>Repositorien</span> Und <span>FIS</span>/<span>CRIS</span>,”</span> December. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14440151">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14440151</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{matthias2025,
  author = {Matthias, Lisa and Pampel, Heinz and Onzie Khamis,
    Christopher},
  title = {Guide {Published:} {Interplay} of {Institutional}
    {Repositories} and {CRIS}},
  date = {2025-07-24},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/n4pnm-vwr12},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-matthias2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Matthias, Lisa, Heinz Pampel, and Christopher Onzie Khamis. 2025.
<span>“Guide Published: Interplay of Institutional Repositories and
CRIS.”</span> July 24, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/n4pnm-vwr12">https://doi.org/10.59350/n4pnm-vwr12</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-24-Guide-Published-Interplay-of-Institutional-Repositories-and-CRIS/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-24-Guide-Published-Interplay-of-Institutional-Repositories-and-CRIS/FIS_Handreichung_Blogpost.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Libraries as operating and preserving institutions for scholarly blogs: Report on a Hands-on Lab at the 113th Bibliocon</title>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Till Stadtbäumer</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Martin Fenner</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Sven Ködel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Charmaine Voigt</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Britta Woldering</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Catharina Ochsner</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Jonas Höfting</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Christopher Onzie Khamis</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-23-Libraries-as-operating-and-preserving-institutions-for-scholarly-blogs/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-23-Libraries-as-operating-and-preserving-institutions-for-scholarly-blogs/IMG_3511.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Scholarly blogs have established themselves as important platforms for making research findings and discourse accessible both within scientific communities and to the general public. Considering the changing social media landscape, the role of non-commercial infrastructures such as blogs or the Fediverse is becoming increasingly important. Blogs can also be seen as part of scholarly-led open access publishing <span class="citation" data-cites="ochsner2025">(Ochsner et al. 2025)</span>.</p>
<p>The long-term accessibility of blogs, especially outside of infrastructures such as <a href="https://de.hypotheses.org/">de.hypotheses.org</a>, is a challenge that has not yet been solved. Archiving dynamic content and comments is a technical and organisational challenge, especially when such content is cited in scientific articles or even court rulings (such as in the <a href="https://verfassungsblog.de">Verfassungsblog</a>). The hacker attacks on the <a href="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</a> in the fall of 2024 furthermore underline the general fragility of digital sources <span class="citation" data-cites="ochsner2025">(Ochsner et al. 2025)</span>.</p>
<p>As part of the <a href="https://bid-kongress2025.de/">BID Congress 2025</a>, the Hands-on Lab ‘Libraries as Operating and Preserving Institutions for Scholarly Blogs’ took place on 26 June in Bremen. The lab was initiated by the project ’Infra Wiss Blogs – Kooperative Informationsinfrastruktur für wissenschaftliche Blogs‘ funded by the German Research Foundation (DFG) <span class="citation" data-cites="ochsner2025">Pampel and Rothfritz (2024)</span>.</p>
<p>The aim of the Hands-on Lab was to bring together experts from the scholarly blogosphere and libraries to discuss the challenges and potential of scholarly blogs with regard to visibility, indexing and long-term accessibility. Using the World Café method, the participants discussed aspects such as technology, organisation and framework conditions for the sustainable safeguarding and visibility of scholarly blogs in moderated discussion rounds, with a particular focus on the role of libraries as potential supporting institutions <span class="citation" data-cites="ochsner2025">(Ochsner et al. 2025)</span>.</p>
<section id="these-1-metadaten-und-licenses" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="these-1-metadaten-und-licenses">These 1: Metadaten und Licenses</h3>
<p>The first thesis was: ‘For the long-term archiving of their publications, scholarly blogs must carry out the necessary preparatory work, such as maintaining metadata and issuing (open) licences.’</p>
<p>The discussion showed that there is often a lack of awareness of these requirements in the blog community. Although blogs are valued as a low-threshold form of communication, it is precisely this low-threshold nature that is in tension with requirements such as metadata maintenance, licensing and technical standardisation.</p>
<p>According to the discussion, the responsibility lies with the blogs or authors - for example with regard to clear licence declarations, clarification of copyright issues (e.g.&nbsp;for embedded images) or the uniform use of CSS classes to support automated import processes. In this context, infrastructure providers, such as libraries, are responsible for providing technical solutions such as plugins to import blog posts into their information systems, as well as providing low-threshold information services.</p>
<p>The extent to which nudging strategies could help to establish more sustainable practices was also discussed. The promotion of open licences was highlighted as a particularly relevant field of action in order to overcome legal challenges in subsequent use, for example in the context of archiving.</p>
</section>
<section id="these-2-cataloguing" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="these-2-cataloguing">These 2: Cataloguing</h3>
<p>The second thesis focused on the cataloguing of scholarly blogs: ‘The cataloguing of scholarly blogs presents libraries with new challenges, as they can only be catalogued to a limited extent using traditional cataloguing criteria.’</p>
<p>The discussion focused on how deeply blogs should be catalogued. The variety of formats - from individual posts and comments to multimedia content - as well as the often multiple authorship lead to uncertainties in library practice.</p>
<p>Technical aspects such as different platforms, software architectures or feed maintenance also make standardisation difficult. The possible use of web scraping or aggregators such as <a href="https://rogue-scholar.org">Rogue Scholar</a> was discussed. The debate was supplemented by considerations on the sustainability of file formats (e.g.&nbsp;PDF-A, HTML), legal categorisation and liability for international content. One thing became clear: A more systematic approach to librarian fields of action in dealing with blogs is needed.</p>
</section>
<section id="these-3-responsibility-and-infrastructure-institutions" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="these-3-responsibility-and-infrastructure-institutions">These 3: Responsibility and Infrastructure Institutions</h3>
<p>The third thesis to be discussed was: “The long-term archiving of scholarly blogs must no longer be treated as a secondary task of public institutions. If necessary, this task must be secured by community-supported platforms.”</p>
<p>This statement was met with broad approval. The focus was on the question of which community can take on this role. Examples from practice showed the commitment of regional depository libraries or specialised information services (FIDs). Several participants reported on ongoing initiatives in their institutions.</p>
<p>Web archiving services and federated models such as <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/activitypub/">ActivityPub</a> were discussed as technical solutions. There was consensus that there is a need for better mapping of existing actors, activities and data flows at the infrastructure level.</p>
</section>
<section id="concluding-discussion" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concluding-discussion">Concluding discussion</h3>
<p>In the final discussion, the question of how a sustainable, community-supported archiving of scholarly blogs could be designed was discussed: centralised through a new software solution or decentralised through stronger integration of existing institutions?</p>
<p>There was a consensus that cooperative models are needed in which different actors take on different roles, for example in metadata management, storage or visibility. A systematic approach was proposed: who is already active, what infrastructures exist and how can a cooperative system be formed from them?</p>
<p>The potential of web archiving was emphasised, especially in combination with targeted metadata extraction. The idea of parallel archiving, by the DNB, discipline-specific FIDs or institutional repositories, met with broad approval.</p>
<p><a href="https://rogue-scholar.org">Rogue Scholar</a> was highlighted as an example of good practice. However, it also became clear that there is still considerable room for improvement in ensuring data flows, e.g.&nbsp;for linking archiving, cataloguing and referencing.</p>
<p>Another topic was the role of scholarly blogs in the reputation system. Some called for blogs to be made more visible and integrated into recognition mechanisms for research evaluation. Others emphasised the independence of blogs, analogous to preprints, but without identical rules.</p>
<p>This led to the central question of definition: When is a blog considered scientific enough? The Infra Wiss Blogs project applies a broad definition: Scholarly blogs can be understood as those blogs that are written by scholars or are concerned with scholarly topics. The participants also favoured an orientation towards relevance rather than formal scientificity.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>
<p>In the Hands-on Lab, there was overwhelming support for a distributed system with various technical and organisational solutions, supported by a committed, interdisciplinary community that takes responsibility for the maintenance and visibility of scholarly blogs.</p>
<p>Further information about the research group can be found on our <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official Website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labelled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
<div id="ref-ochsner2025" class="csl-entry">
Ochsner, Catharina, Elena Di Rosa, Martin Fenner, Sven Ködel, Heinz Pampel, Britta Woldering, Till Stadtbäumer, Charmaine Voigt, and Jonas Höfting. 2025. <span>“Bibliotheken Als Betreibende Und Bewahrende Institutionen Für Wissenschaftliche Blogs.”</span> In. <a href="https://nbn-resolving.org/urn:nbn:de:0290-opus4-194690">https://nbn-resolving.org/urn:nbn:de:0290-opus4-194690</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-pampel2024" class="csl-entry">
Pampel, Heinz, and Laura Rothfritz. 2024. <span>“Kooperative Informationsinfrastruktur Für Wissenschaftliche Blogs (Infra Wiss Blogs).”</span> <em>Zenodo</em>, August. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13234482">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13234482</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{pampel2025,
  author = {Pampel, Heinz and Stadtbäumer, Till and Fenner, Martin and
    Ködel, Sven and Voigt, Charmaine and Woldering, Britta and Ochsner,
    Catharina and Höfting, Jonas and Onzie Khamis, Christopher},
  title = {Libraries as Operating and Preserving Institutions for
    Scholarly Blogs: {Report} on a {Hands-on} {Lab} at the 113th
    {Bibliocon}},
  date = {2025-07-23},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/xqwyd-0g579},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-pampel2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Pampel, Heinz, Till Stadtbäumer, Martin Fenner, Sven Ködel, Charmaine
Voigt, Britta Woldering, Catharina Ochsner, Jonas Höfting, and
Christopher Onzie Khamis. 2025. <span>“Libraries as Operating and
Preserving Institutions for Scholarly Blogs: Report on a Hands-on Lab at
the 113th Bibliocon.”</span> July 23, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/xqwyd-0g579">https://doi.org/10.59350/xqwyd-0g579</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-23-Libraries-as-operating-and-preserving-institutions-for-scholarly-blogs/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-23-Libraries-as-operating-and-preserving-institutions-for-scholarly-blogs/IMG_3511.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>BUA fellowship: Metadata flows in the context of research data</title>
  <dc:creator>Dorothea Strecker</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-18-BUA-Fellowship-Metadata-flows-in-the-context-of-research-data/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-18-BUA-Fellowship-Metadata-flows-in-the-context-of-research-data/fellowship_program.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>In my PhD research, I investigate how metadata for research data are generated and maintained. I have started by analyzing how metadata records of the DOI registration agency DataCite change over time <span class="citation" data-cites="strecker_changes_2024 strecker_how_2024">(Strecker 2024a, 2024b)</span>. Recently, I was awarded a grant by the Berlin University Alliance (BUA) - through the <a href="https://www.berlin-university-alliance.de/en/commitments/research-quality/forschung/fellowship/index.html">BUA Fellowship Program of the Objective 3 - Advancing Research Quality and Value</a>. This grant will allow me to visit Stefanie Haustein, associate professor at the School of Information Studies at the University of Ottawa and co-director of the <a href="https://www.scholcommlab.ca">ScholCommLab</a>. During my stay, I will investigate metadata flows in the context of research data. In particular, I will examine the transfer of metadata from local to global contexts.</p>
<section id="metadata-flows-in-the-context-of-research-data" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="metadata-flows-in-the-context-of-research-data">Metadata flows in the context of research data</h3>
<p>Research data are typically deposited in research data repositories - infrastructures that specialize in handling this resource type. Metadata describing the datasets are also generated and maintained at these infrastructures. Numerous standards - metadata schemas - are used to describe research data <span class="citation" data-cites="asok_common_2024 koshoffer_giving_2018">(Asok et al. 2024; Koshoffer et al. 2018)</span>. Even within a discipline, the use of metadata schemas is not uniform <span class="citation" data-cites="mayernik_role_2022">(Mayernik and Liapich 2022)</span>. This variance arises because research data repositories create metadata for different use cases. On the one hand, metadata are needed to describe research data in a general and homogeneous way - for example, to enable data discovery in large search services. On the other hand, researchers need subject-specific metadata in order to be able to make an informed decision about whether they want to reuse a dataset <span class="citation" data-cites="de_vries_flexible_2022 doran_reconciling_2021 sostek_discovering_2024">(De Vries et al. 2022; Doran, Edmond, and Nugent-Folan 2021; Sostek et al. 2024)</span>. In order to cover this range of requirements, many research data repositories use several metadata schemas in parallel, e.g.&nbsp;the general DataCite metadata schema for DOI registration and a specialized schema adressing the needs of local users <span class="citation" data-cites="habermann_connecting_2023 lee_landscape_2019 wu_analysis_2023">(Habermann 2023; Lee and Jeng 2019; Wu et al. 2023)</span>. In research data repositories, metadata are often initially generated based on a locally implemented, specific metadata schema. Metadata are then mapped to a general schema to meet global requirements such as DOI registration or harvesting <span class="citation" data-cites="habermann_connecting_2023">(Habermann 2023)</span>. During these mapping processes, however, information from the original comprehensive description can be lost <span class="citation" data-cites="radio_manifestations_2017 taylor_think_2022">(Radio et al. 2017; Taylor et al. 2022)</span>. As a result, metadata lose completeness when they are transferred from local to global contexts <span class="citation" data-cites="mayernik_role_2022">(Mayernik and Liapich 2022)</span>.</p>
<p>During the fellowship, I will investigate metadata flows from research data repositories to DataCite. The aim is to determine whether information that is missing in DataCite metadata are also missing in local contexts or would be available but are not transmitted.</p>
</section>
<section id="why-this-matters" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-this-matters">Why this matters</h3>
<p>Complete metadata are necessary to convey the context of research data. This is relevant for many interactions with research data, including discovery, reuse and citation. Bibliometric research in particular is hindered by incomplete metadata, as is the development of metrics that are intended to reflect the impact of research data <span class="citation" data-cites="ninkov_datasets_2021">(Ninkov et al. 2021)</span>. This research will assess the potential of an approach to improve metadata quality - the optimization of mappings to the DataCite metadata schema.</p>
<p>Further information about our research group can be found on our <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labelled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
<div id="ref-asok_common_2024" class="csl-entry">
Asok, Kavya, Sushree Snigdha Dandpat, Dinesh K. Gupta, and Prashant Shrivastava. 2024. <span>“Common <span>Metadata</span> <span>Framework</span> for <span>Research</span> <span>Data</span> <span>Repository</span>: <span>Necessity</span> to <span>Support</span> <span>Open</span> <span>Science</span>.”</span> <em>Journal of Library Metadata</em> 24: 1–13. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/19386389.2024.2329370">https://doi.org/10.1080/19386389.2024.2329370</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-de_vries_flexible_2022" class="csl-entry">
De Vries, Jerry, Vyacheslav Tykhonov, Andrea Scharnhorst, Eko Indarto, Femmy Admiraal, and Mike Priddy. 2022. <span>“Flexible <span>Metadata</span> <span>Schemes</span> for <span>Research</span> <span>Data</span> <span>Repositories</span>.<span>The</span> <span>Common</span> <span>Framework</span> in <span>Dataverse</span> and the <span>CMDI</span> <span>Use</span> <span>Case</span>.”</span> In, 168–80. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3384/ecp18915">https://doi.org/10.3384/ecp18915</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-doran_reconciling_2021" class="csl-entry">
Doran, Michelle, Jennifer Edmond, and Georgina Nugent-Folan. 2021. <span>“Reconciling the <span>Cultural</span> <span>Complexity</span> of <span>Research</span> <span>Data</span>: <span>Can</span> We <span>Make</span> <span>Data</span> <span>Interdisciplinary</span> Without <span>Hiding</span> <span>Disciplinary</span> <span>Knowledge</span>.”</span> <a href="http://www.tara.tcd.ie/handle/2262/83156">http://www.tara.tcd.ie/handle/2262/83156</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-habermann_connecting_2023" class="csl-entry">
Habermann, Ted. 2023. <span>“Connecting <span>Repositories</span> to the <span>Global</span> <span>Research</span> <span>Community</span>: <span>A</span> <span>Re</span>-<span>Curation</span> <span>Process</span>.”</span> <em>Journal of eScience Librarianship</em> 12 (3): e739. <a href="https://doi.org/10.7191/jeslib.739">https://doi.org/10.7191/jeslib.739</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-koshoffer_giving_2018" class="csl-entry">
Koshoffer, Amy, Amy E. Neeser, Linda Newman, and Lisa R. Johnston. 2018. <span>“Giving <span>Datasets</span> <span>Context</span>: A <span>Comparison</span> <span>Study</span> of <span>Institutional</span> <span>Repositories</span> That <span>Apply</span> <span>Varying</span> <span>Degrees</span> of <span>Curation</span>.”</span> <em>International Journal of Digital Curation</em> 13 (1): 15–34. <a href="https://doi.org/10.2218/ijdc.v13i1.632">https://doi.org/10.2218/ijdc.v13i1.632</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-lee_landscape_2019" class="csl-entry">
Lee, Jian‐Sin, and Wei Jeng. 2019. <span>“The Landscape of Archived Studies in a Social Science Data Infrastructure: <span>Investigating</span> the <span>ICPSR</span> Metadata Records.”</span> <em>Proceedings of the Association for Information Science and Technology</em> 56 (1): 147–56. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/pra2.62">https://doi.org/10.1002/pra2.62</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-mayernik_role_2022" class="csl-entry">
Mayernik, Matthew S., and Yauheniya Liapich. 2022. <span>“The <span>Role</span> of <span>Metadata</span> and <span>Vocabulary</span> <span>Standards</span> in <span>Enabling</span> <span>Scientific</span> <span>Data</span> <span>Interoperability</span>: <span>A</span> <span>Study</span> of <span>Earth</span> <span>System</span> <span>Science</span> <span>Data</span> <span>Facilities</span>.”</span> <em>Journal of eScience Librarianship</em> 11 (2). <a href="https://doi.org/10.7191/jeslib.619">https://doi.org/10.7191/jeslib.619</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-ninkov_datasets_2021" class="csl-entry">
Ninkov, Anton Boudreau, Kathleen Gregory, Isabella Peters, and Stefanie Haustein. 2021. <span>“Datasets on <span>DataCite</span> - an <span>Initial</span> <span>Bibliometric</span> <span>Investigation</span>.”</span> In. Leuven, Belgium (Virtual). <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4730857">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4730857</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-radio_manifestations_2017" class="csl-entry">
Radio, Erik, Fernando Rios, Jeffrey C. Oliver, Benjamin Hickson, and Niamh Wallace. 2017. <span>“Manifestations of <span>Metadata</span> <span>Structures</span> in <span>Research</span> <span>Datasets</span> and <span>Their</span> <span>Ontic</span> <span>Implications</span>.”</span> <em>Journal of Library Metadata</em> 17 (3-4): 161–82. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/19386389.2018.1439278">https://doi.org/10.1080/19386389.2018.1439278</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-sostek_discovering_2024" class="csl-entry">
Sostek, Katrina, Daniel Russell, Nitesh Goyal, Tarfah Alrashed, Stella Dugall, and Natasha Noy. 2024. <span>“Discovering <span>Datasets</span> on the <span>Web</span> <span>Scale</span>: <span>Challenges</span> and <span>Recommendations</span> for <span>Google</span> <span>Dataset</span> <span>Search</span>.”</span> <em>Harvard Data Science Review</em> Special Issue 4. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1162/99608f92.4c3e11ca">https://doi.org/10.1162/99608f92.4c3e11ca</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-strecker_changes_2024" class="csl-entry">
Strecker, Dorothea. 2024a. <span>“Changes in <span>DataCite</span> <span>DOI</span> Metadata for Research Data.”</span> Zenodo. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14274240">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14274240</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-strecker_how_2024" class="csl-entry">
———. 2024b. <span>“How Permanent Are Metadata for Research Data? <span>Understanding</span> Changes in <span>DataCite</span> <span>DOI</span> Metadata.”</span> arXiv. <a href="https://doi.org/10.48550/arxiv.2412.05128">https://doi.org/10.48550/arxiv.2412.05128</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-taylor_think_2022" class="csl-entry">
Taylor, Shawna, Sarah Wright, Mikala R. Narlock, and Ted Habermann. 2022. <span>“Think <span>Globally</span>, <span>Act</span> <span>Locally</span>: <span>The</span> <span>Importance</span> of <span>Elevating</span> <span>Data</span> <span>Repository</span> <span>Metadata</span> to the <span>Global</span> <span>Infrastructure</span>.”</span> In. <a href="https://hdl.handle.net/11299/228001">https://hdl.handle.net/11299/228001</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-wu_analysis_2023" class="csl-entry">
Wu, Mingfang, Stephen M. Richard, Chantelle Verhey, Leyla Jael Castro, Baptiste Cecconi, and Nick Juty. 2023. <span>“An <span>Analysis</span> of <span>Crosswalks</span> from <span>Research</span> <span>Data</span> <span>Schemas</span> to <span>Schema</span>.org.”</span> <em>Data Intelligence</em> 5 (1): 100–121. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1162/dint_a_00186">https://doi.org/10.1162/dint_a_00186</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{strecker2025,
  author = {Strecker, Dorothea},
  title = {BUA Fellowship: {Metadata} Flows in the Context of Research
    Data},
  date = {2025-07-18},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/wwwj7-4cm07},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-strecker2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Strecker, Dorothea. 2025. <span>“BUA Fellowship: Metadata Flows in the
Context of Research Data .”</span> July 18, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/wwwj7-4cm07">https://doi.org/10.59350/wwwj7-4cm07</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-18-BUA-Fellowship-Metadata-flows-in-the-context-of-research-data/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-18-BUA-Fellowship-Metadata-flows-in-the-context-of-research-data/fellowship_program.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Connecting Knowledge with Wikidata: A Practical Project with the Museum für Naturkunde Berlin</title>
  <dc:creator>Laura Rothfritz</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Stefanie Paß</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Sabine von Mering</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Clara Schindler</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-16-Connecting-Knowledge-with-Wikidata-a-practical-Project-with-the-Museum-fuer-Naturkunde-Berlin/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>How can scholarly publications be made more visible, discoverable, and interconnected? This question is the focus of a student practical project conducted as part of the seminar within the module Information Production and Management (BP3) in the summer semester 2025.</p>
<p>In close collaboration with colleagues from the <a href="https://www.museumfuernaturkunde.berlin/de/forschung/bibliothek">Coordination Office for Scholarly Publishing at the Library</a> as well as a research associate from the “Future of Collections” research area at the Museum für Naturkunde Berlin (MfN), the students are working on an exciting task: documenting scholarly journals in Wikidata from the fields of zoology, biodiversity research, and paleontology, including taxonomy and systematics of fossil organisms, enriching them with information, and linking them to each other.</p>
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-16-Connecting-Knowledge-with-Wikidata-a-practical-Project-with-the-Museum-fuer-Naturkunde-Berlin/mfn_visit.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>As part of this semester’s “Übung”, students received an introduction to Linked Open Data, with a particular focus on Wikidata. Especially for library applications, Wikidata is an exciting project because authorities, publications, and collections can be linked together, creating new opportunities for discovery, contextualization, and visibility.</p>
<p>The students worked with real datasets on the Museum für Naturkunde’s in-house journals <a href="https://zse.pensoft.net/">Zoosystematics and Evolution (ZSE)</a>, <a href="https://fr.pensoft.net/">Fossil Record (FR)</a> and <a href="https://dez.pensoft.net/">Deutsche Entomologische Zeitschrift (DEZ)</a>. Among other tasks, their work involved reviewing existing Wikidata entries, adding missing information, and linking relevant metadata (for example ISSNs, publishers, publication periods) with authority records such as the <a href="https://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/">Biodiversity Heritage Library (BHL)</a>, the <a href="https://gnd.network/Webs/gnd/DE/Entdecken/entdecken_node.html">Gemeinsame Normdatei (GND)</a>, or the <a href="https://viaf.org/de">Virtual International Authority File (VIAF)</a>.</p>
<p>The module at the Institute for Library and Information Science also included a visit to the Museum für Naturkunde, where students received a tour of the collections. This provided a hands-on introduction to working with real museum objects as part of their data-related assignments.</p>
<p>The edit-a-thon, embedded in a university seminar, demonstrated impressively the potential of structured, machine-readable data for digital science communication. Through the targeted recording and interlinking of publication data in Wikidata, new possibilities emerge for analysis and visualization. Tools like <a href="https://scholia.toolforge.org/">Scholia</a> already offer fascinating insights into topics such as “Top Topics through Time,” author networks, or gender ratios in science.</p>
<p>Examples from Scholia for individual publication periods of the three journals:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>ZSE (2008–present): <a href="https://scholia.toolforge.org/venue/Q15755646" class="uri">https://scholia.toolforge.org/venue/Q15755646</a></p></li>
<li><p>FR (2008–present): <a href="https://scholia.toolforge.org/venue/Q2455930" class="uri">https://scholia.toolforge.org/venue/Q2455930</a></p></li>
<li><p>DEZ (1954–present): <a href="https://scholia.toolforge.org/venue/Q403726">https://scholia.toolforge.org/venue/Q4037265</a></p></li>
</ul>
<p>By systematically capturing article data from more than 160 years of publishing activity, a valuable resource is created for future research questions. Scholarly publications serve here as references and as data sources, but also as links to other entities such as groups of organisms, people, places, research expeditions, and collections (von Mering, 2024). The overarching goal is an open knowledge infrastructure for everyone, both researchers and the broader public. The Museum für Naturkunde Berlin will continue along this path with its own digitization initiatives and in collaboration with external partner projects.</p>
<p>Further information: Post about Open Cultural Data in Wikimedia Germany’s blog: <a href="https://blog.wikimedia.de/2024/04/22/wie-das-naturkundemuseum-mit-linked-open-data-unbekannte-forschende-sichtbar-macht/">Wie das Naturkundemuseum mit Linked Open Data unbekannte Forschende sichtbar macht</a></p>
<p>Further information about the research group can be found on our <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labelled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
<div id="ref-10.3897/rio.10.e118851" class="csl-entry">
von Mering, Sabine, Erik Stolze, Katja Kaiser, and Mareike Petersen. 2024. <span>“Sharing Data, Caring for Collections. <span>Open</span> Data on Collection Agents Affiliated with the <span>Museum</span> f<span>ü</span>r <span>Naturkunde Berlin</span>.”</span> <em>Research Ideas and Outcomes</em> 10: e118851. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3897/rio.10.e118851">https://doi.org/10.3897/rio.10.e118851</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{rothfritz2025,
  author = {Rothfritz, Laura and Paß, Stefanie and von Mering, Sabine
    and Schindler, Clara and Pampel, Heinz},
  title = {Connecting {Knowledge} with {Wikidata:} {A} {Practical}
    {Project} with the {Museum} Für {Naturkunde} {Berlin}},
  date = {2025-07-16},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/hzjde-ss694},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-rothfritz2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Rothfritz, Laura, Stefanie Paß, Sabine von Mering, Clara Schindler, and
Heinz Pampel. 2025. <span>“Connecting Knowledge with Wikidata: A
Practical Project with the Museum Für Naturkunde Berlin.”</span> July
16, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/hzjde-ss694">https://doi.org/10.59350/hzjde-ss694</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Teaching</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-16-Connecting-Knowledge-with-Wikidata-a-practical-Project-with-the-Museum-fuer-Naturkunde-Berlin/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-16-Connecting-Knowledge-with-Wikidata-a-practical-Project-with-the-Museum-fuer-Naturkunde-Berlin/mfn_visit.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Networking for the Advancement of Institutional Open Access Repositories in Germany</title>
  <dc:creator>Lisa Matthias</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Christopher Onzie Khamis</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-06-23-Networking-for-the-Advancement-of-Institutional-OA-Repositories/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>We are excited to share our first guide from the BMFTR-funded (Federal Ministry for Research, Technology and Space) project “Professionalisierung der Open-Access-Repositorien-Infrastruktur in Deutschland (Pro OAR DE)”: “Preprints: Handlungsfeld für institutionelle Open-Access-Repositorien” (German only.)</p>
<p>Matthias, L., Pampel, H., Khamis, C. O., Rothfritz, L., &amp; Wrzesinski, M. (2025). <em>Preprints: Handlungsfeld für institutionelle Open-Access-Repositorien. Pro OAR DE Handreichung.</em> Zenodo. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15603096" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15603096</a></p>
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-06-23-Networking-for-the-Advancement-of-Institutional-OA-Repositories/Blogpost_Preprint_Handreichung.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>This publication stems from our November 13, 2024 <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/infomanagement/events/prooarde-preprints">networking forum</a> on preprints and institutional repositories, which brought together 59 Open Access professionals from across Germany. The guide captures the collective expertise and insights generated during this collaborative event, offering practical recommendations to enhance how institutional repositories handle preprints.</p>
<p>Following expert presentations by <a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7060-3670">Lea-Maria Ferguson</a> (Helmholtz Open Science Office) and <a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9846-5516">Alexander Wagner</a> (DESY), participants engaged in dynamic discussions in a “world café” format where they shared experiences and developed solutions to common obstacles. The presentation slides are available <a href="https://zenodo.org/doi/10.5281/zenodo.14185122">online</a>.</p>
<hr>
<p>The guide distills these rich discussions into actionable recommendations across five critical areas for repository managers:</p>
<section id="policy-for-preprints" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="policy-for-preprints">1. Policy for Preprints</h3>
<p>Without overarching standards, institutions struggle with unclear definitions distinguishing publication types. Proposed solutions include establishing clear typological classifications at submission, setting explicit criteria for different preprint versions, implementing automated notification systems for updates, and creating robust links between preprints and their final published versions.</p>
</section>
<section id="accessibility-workflows" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="accessibility-workflows">2. Accessibility Workflows</h3>
<p>Repository managers face a complex web of challenges: the relationship between institutional and subject-specific repositories, technical representation issues, and limited researcher awareness about the strategic implications of preprints. Solutions include fostering cross-institutional dialogue, setting focused goals to reduce maintenance overhead, and providing comprehensive consultation services that empower researchers to make informed publication decisions.</p>
</section>
<section id="versioning" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="versioning">3. Versioning</h3>
<p>Three major barriers complicate version management: First, many repository systems simply lack versioning functionalities. Second, those with versioning capabilities must navigate the trade-off between merge approaches and split approaches. Third, authors have no obligation to report when their preprints are subsequently published, making it difficult to track version evolution. The community strongly advocated for early publication counseling and proactive author engagement to map out publication trajectories and develop appropriate pathways collaboratively.</p>
</section>
<section id="disciplinary-diversity" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="disciplinary-diversity">4. Disciplinary Diversity</h3>
<p>Preprint definitions and practices vary across disciplines, creating workflow complexities that require tailored solutions and generating reporting issues when publications appear across multiple platforms and stages. This diversity demands flexible approaches: facilitating faculty-level decision-making, establishing discipline-specific editorial networks for quality assurance, and emphasizing the critical role of high-quality metadata.</p>
</section>
<section id="further-challenges" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="further-challenges">5. Further Challenges</h3>
<p>Communication barriers with publishers (particularly in the humanities), absent technical standards for metadata transfer and linking, and limited training opportunities for repository managers continue to hinder progress. Highlighted solutions include targeted outreach to academic communities, developing robust technical interfaces for better interoperability, establishing preprint policies with clear Persistent identifier (PID) recommendations, and expanding professional development programs both nationally and internationally.</p>
<hr>
<p>This guide provides a foundation for continued professional exchange. Repository operators, libraries, and institutional decision-makers will find valuable insights for strategically embedding preprints within their institutions.</p>
<p>We extend our sincere thanks to all forum participants who contributed their expertise and experience to this collaborative effort. We welcome your feedback and look forward to continuing this important dialogue as we collectively strengthen the Open Access repository landscape.</p>
<p>The Pro OAR DE project continues with its sixth Networking Forum on July 7, 2025, focusing on “Compliance with Funding Requirements for Open Access.” We are delighted to welcome representatives from the European Research Council (ERC) and the German Research Foundation (Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft, DFG), who will provide insights into their repository strategies and Open Access policies. <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/infomanagement/events/prooarde-compliance">Registration</a> is now open for this virtual event.</p>
<p>For more information about Pro OAR DE and our upcoming activities, please visit our official <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/infomanagement/projekte/pro-oar-de">website</a>. This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labeled sections – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.en">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
<div id="ref-matthias_preprints_2025" class="csl-entry">
Matthias, Lisa, Heinz Pampel, Christopher Onzie Khamis, Laura Rothfritz, and Marcel Wrzesinski. 2025. <span>“Preprints: <span>Handlungsfeld</span> Für Institutionelle <span>Open</span>-<span>Access</span>-<span>Repositorien</span>. <span>Pro</span> <span>OAR</span> <span>DE</span> <span>Handreichung</span>.”</span> Zenodo. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15603096">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15603096</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-wrzesinski_pro_2024" class="csl-entry">
Wrzesinski, Marcel, Alexander Wagner, Lea-Maria Ferguson, and Marcel Meistring. 2024. <span>“Pro <span>OAR</span> <span>DE</span> <span>Vernetzungsforum</span>: <span>Institutionelle</span> <span>Repositorien</span> Und <span>Preprints</span>,”</span> November. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14185122">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14185122</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{matthias2025,
  author = {Matthias, Lisa and Pampel, Heinz and Onzie Khamis,
    Christopher},
  title = {Networking for the {Advancement} of {Institutional} {Open}
    {Access} {Repositories} in {Germany}},
  date = {2025-06-23},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/kb3zc-v2x38},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-matthias2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Matthias, Lisa, Heinz Pampel, and Christopher Onzie Khamis. 2025.
<span>“Networking for the Advancement of Institutional Open Access
Repositories in Germany.”</span> June 23, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/kb3zc-v2x38">https://doi.org/10.59350/kb3zc-v2x38</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-06-23-Networking-for-the-Advancement-of-Institutional-OA-Repositories/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jun 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-06-23-Networking-for-the-Advancement-of-Institutional-OA-Repositories/Blogpost_Preprint_Handreichung.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Recap: Infra Wiss Blogs Webinar on Rogue Scholar</title>
  <dc:creator>Jonas Höfting</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Catharina Ochsner</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-06-19-Recap-Infra-Wiss-Blogs-Webinar-on-Rogue-Scholar/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="presentations" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="presentations">Presentations</h2>
<p>On June 11, 2025, the webinar of the project <a href="https://infrawissblogs.org/">Infra Wiss Blogs</a> funded by the German Research Foundation (DFG) took place on the topic of “Blog archiving with Rogue Scholar using the example of WordPress hosted blogs”. The webinar highlighted the possibilities and challenges of archiving scholarly blogs. At its core was the presentation of <a href="https://rogue-scholar.org/">Rogue Scholar</a>, a platform for archiving scholarly blogs. Around 50 people took part. This blog post summarizes the key discussion points and findings from the webinar.</p>
<p>After a welcome by <a href="https://heinzpampel.de/">Heinz Pampel</a>, <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/infomanagement/teaminfomanagement">Catharina Ochsner</a> first introduced the topic of scholarly blogs. She introduced the basic concept of scholarly blogging, presented challenges of archiving blogs, and emphasized the importance of the long-term accessibility of scholarly blogs. <span class="citation" data-cites="ochsner_blogarchivierung_2025">(Ochsner and Pampel 2025)</span>.</p>
<p>Martin Fenner (<a href="https://front-matter.io/team">Front Matter</a> then presented the functionality and possibilities of <a href="https://rogue-scholar.org/">Rogue Scholar</a>, a platform based on <a href="https://inveniosoftware.org/products/rdm/">Invenio RDM</a>, which is dedicated to archiving scholarly blogs. Rogue Scholar not only archives the content of the blogs, but also assigns Digital Object Identifiers (DOIs) for blog posts and ensures web archiving via the <a href="https://archive.org/about/">Internet Archive</a>. Currently, around 150 blogs and more than 40,000 posts are archived at Rogue Scholar. All blogs archived by Rogue Scholar are licensed under <a href="https://creativecommons.org/share-your-work/">Creative Commons</a> Attribution (CC-BY). To facilitate the archiving of blogs at Rogue Scholar, Martin Fenner made a number of recommendations, such as the use of a CC-BY license or the use of references in the blog posts <span class="citation" data-cites="fenner_blogarchivierung_2025">(Fenner 2025)</span>.</p>
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-06-19-Recap-Infra-Wiss-Blogs-Webinar-on-Rogue-Scholar/webinar_infrawissblogs.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Afterwards, <a href="https://blog.dini.de/EPub_FIS/author/beucked/">Daniel Beucke</a> from the <a href="https://www02.sub.uni-goettingen.de/en/news/">Göttingen State and University Library (SUB)</a> and <a href="https://zfmedienwissenschaft.de/archiv/autorin/steiner-tobias">Tobias Steiner</a> shared their experiences with Rogue Scholar and the associated archiving of their scholarly blogs.</p>
<p>Daniel Beucke contributed the perspective of the <a href="https://blog.dini.de/EPub_FIS/">DINI blog</a>, which has been reporting from the working groups of the <a href="https://dini.de/">German Initiative for Network Information (DINI)</a> since 2016. He emphasized the relevance of long-term availability and described the simple integration into Rogue Scholar. According to Beucke, a central challenge for the DINI blog is the high number of guest authors and their representation in the metadata <span class="citation" data-cites="beucke_anwenderperspektive_2025">(Beucke 2025)</span>. Tobias Steiner contributed his experience from two perspectives: He not only blogs privately on <a href="https://flavoursofopen.science/">Flavours of Open</a>, but is also an editor for the blog of the open access journal <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/home/CST">Critical Studies in Television</a>, <a href="https://cstonline.net/">CSTonline</a> <span class="citation" data-cites="steiner_archivierung_2025">(Steiner 2025)</span>. Both blogs are archived on Rogue Scholar.</p>
</section>
<section id="discussion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="discussion">Discussion</h2>
<p>In the final discussion, a number of themes and questions emerged, which are summarized here.</p>
<p>A first central point of discussion was the use of CC licenses for scholarly blogs. As mentioned above, Rogue Scholar only archives blogs whose posts are published under a CC-BY license. CC-BY can be seen as the standard for open access publications, as this license entails few restrictions and also corresponds most closely to the scholarly citation practice. However, subsequent archiving can lead to complex situations if blog posts in community blogs have not yet been published under an open license. In such cases, all previous authors must be contacted in order to enable subsequent licensing. It is therefore recommended that both the blog and each individual post be clearly licensed in advance.</p>
<p>Technical challenges were also discussed, such as dealing with multimedia content or comments in blogs. Unresolved issues became clear here. The role of scholarly blogs in the publication landscape was considered from several perspectives. Similarities between blog posts and pre-prints were highlighted. Martin Fenner reported on the first successful tests with peer review procedures for blog posts via the platform <a href="https://cms.metaror.org/">MetaROR</a> <span class="citation" data-cites="marcum_peer-review_2025">(Marcum 2025)</span>. The possibility of mapping corrections and retractions of blog posts was also discussed.</p>
<p>In the context of archiving scholarlyblogs, the structural dependence on individual actors was identified as a problem. Two strategies for enabling long-term accessibility emerged from the discussion: firstly, the collective assumption of responsibility through community-supported infrastructures, and secondly, the institutional anchoring of blog offerings within established organizations.</p>
</section>
<section id="summary-and-outlook" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary-and-outlook">Summary and outlook</h2>
<p>The webinar provided insights into both the functioning of Rogue Scholar and the perspectives of its users. The positive response as well as the large number of questions and discussions illustrate the existing need within the scholarly community. At the same time, it became clear that projects such as Infra Wiss Blogs can make an important contribution to structuring discourse on cooperative solutions for digital preservation.</p>
<p>We would like to thank all speakers and participants for their contributions and the insightful discussions. The slide sets of the speakers are available in the <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/infomanagement">Community of the Chair of Information Management on Zenodo</a>. We communicate updates on the project and other events via this blog, the <a href="https://infrawissblogs.org/">project blog</a> and the project’s <a href="https://www.listserv.dfn.de/sympa/info/infra-wiss-blogs">mailing list</a>.</p>
<p>Further information about our group can be found on the <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labeled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
<div id="ref-beucke_anwenderperspektive_2025" class="csl-entry">
Beucke, Daniel. 2025. <span>“Anwenderperspektive: <span>DINI</span>-Blog.”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15640226">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15640226</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-fenner_blogarchivierung_2025" class="csl-entry">
Fenner, Martin. 2025. <span>“Blogarchivierung von <span>WordPress</span> Mit Rogue Scholar.”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15640360">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15640360</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-marcum_peer-review_2025" class="csl-entry">
Marcum, Christopher Steven. 2025. <span>“Peer-Review for a Blog Post? My Experience with <span>MetaROR</span>.”</span> <em>Upstream</em>, April. <a href="https://doi.org/10.54900/bymaz-4fw37">https://doi.org/10.54900/bymaz-4fw37</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-ochsner_blogarchivierung_2025" class="csl-entry">
Ochsner, Catharina, and Heinz Pampel. 2025. <span>“Blogarchivierung Mit Rogue Scholar Am Beispiel von <span>WordPress</span> Gehosteten Blogs.”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15640371">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15640371</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-steiner_archivierung_2025" class="csl-entry">
Steiner, Tobias. 2025. <span>“Archivierug von Blogs in Rogue Scholar – Zwei Beispiele Aus Der Community.”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15640396">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15640396</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{höfting2025,
  author = {Höfting, Jonas and Ochsner, Catharina and Pampel, Heinz},
  title = {Recap: {Infra} {Wiss} {Blogs} {Webinar} on {Rogue} {Scholar}},
  date = {2025-06-19},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/5azm1-a0n89},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-höfting2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Höfting, Jonas, Catharina Ochsner, and Heinz Pampel. 2025. <span>“Recap:
Infra Wiss Blogs Webinar on Rogue Scholar.”</span> June 19, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/5azm1-a0n89">https://doi.org/10.59350/5azm1-a0n89</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-06-19-Recap-Infra-Wiss-Blogs-Webinar-on-Rogue-Scholar/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-06-19-Recap-Infra-Wiss-Blogs-Webinar-on-Rogue-Scholar/webinar_infrawissblogs.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="94" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Open Access Dashboard Collection Launched</title>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Johannes Schneider</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-06-12-Open-Access-Dashboard-Collection-Launched/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="open-access-dashboard-collection-launched" class="level1">
<h1>Open Access Dashboard Collection Launched</h1>
<p>As Open Access becomes increasingly central to scholarship and science policy, understanding the proportion of open publications within the overall publication output, whether at the level of research-performing organizations, individual countries, or globally, is gaining importance.</p>
<p>In recent years, an increasing number of dashboards have been created to track different facets of Open Access. Yet, a comprehensive overview of these tools has been missing. In our project <a href="https://oa-datenpraxis.de/en/">OA Datenpraxis</a> (Data Practice for Shaping the Open Access Transformation – Analysis, Recommendation, Training &amp; Networking), funded by the <a href="https://www.dfg.de/">German Research Foundation (DFG)</a> <span class="citation" data-cites="pampel_datenpraxis_2024">(Pampel et al. 2024)</span>, we have spent the past several months engaging with this topic by systematically mapping and analyzing the current landscape of Open Access dashboards.</p>
<p>We conducted a survey in which we identified nearly 60 dashboards. To enable a structured description of these dashboards, we developed a dedicated <a href="https://oa-datenpraxis.de/dashboards_schema.html">metadata schema</a>. This schema captures key characteristics such as data sources, their license, responsible organizations, the type of output they monitor and more.</p>
<p>The resulting <a href="https://oa-datenpraxis.de/en/dashboard_uebersicht.html">Open Access Dashboard Collection</a> is now available on the project website. The underlying <a href="https://oa-datenpraxis.de/dashboards_schema.html">metadata schema</a> is also accessible there and open for reuse.</p>
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-06-12-Open-Access-Dashboard-Collection-Launched/oa-dashboard-collection.jpeg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>We aim to continue developing this dataset through an open and participatory process. We welcome suggestions for additional dashboards as well as ideas for further refining the dataset and its structure.</p>
<p>An editable version of the collection is available in a <a href="https://nextcloud.gfz.de/s/QG38J6kEDbJ8DXz">shared Nextcloud folder</a>, where you can directly add your suggestions. For questions, feedback, or submissions, please contact us at: <a href="mailto:oa-datenpraxis-dashboards@listserv.dfn.de">oa-datenpraxis-dashboards@listserv.dfn.de</a>. We look forward to hearing from you!</p>
<p>The project OA Datenpraxis supports the development of infrastructures for the open access transformation at research institutions in Germany. It focuses on promoting and establishing sovereign data practices to shape and manage this transformation effectively.</p>
<p>Further information about the project can be found on the <a href="https://oa-datenpraxis.de/en">project website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labeled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
<div id="ref-pampel_datenpraxis_2024" class="csl-entry">
Pampel, Heinz, Najko Jahn, Roland Bertelmann, Wolfram Horstmann, Laura Rothfritz, Lea Maria Ferguson, Birgit Schmidt, and Anna Stisser. 2024. <span>“Datenpraxis Zur <span>Gestaltung</span> Der <span>Open</span>-<span>Access</span>-<span>Transformation</span> - <span>Analyse</span>, <span>Empfehlung</span>, <span>Training</span> &amp; <span>Vernetzung</span> (<span>OA</span> <span>Datenpraxis</span>).”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.10794298">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.10794298</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{pampel2025,
  author = {Pampel, Heinz and Schneider, Johannes},
  title = {Open {Access} {Dashboard} {Collection} {Launched}},
  date = {2025-06-12},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/gj3rx-m5059},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-pampel2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Pampel, Heinz, and Johannes Schneider. 2025. <span>“Open Access
Dashboard Collection Launched.”</span> June 12, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/gj3rx-m5059">https://doi.org/10.59350/gj3rx-m5059</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-06-12-Open-Access-Dashboard-Collection-Launched/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-06-12-Open-Access-Dashboard-Collection-Launched/oa-dashboard-collection.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Rückblick: OA Datenpraxis Webinar zu offenen Metadaten für Hochschulrankings am Beispiel des Leiden Ranking</title>
  <dc:creator>Sophia Dörner</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-06-11-Rueckblick-OA-Datenpraxis-Webinar-zu-offenen-Metadaten-fuer-Hochschulrankings/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-06-11-Rueckblick-OA-Datenpraxis-Webinar-zu-offenen-Metadaten-fuer-Hochschulrankings/logo_oa_datenpraxis(2).png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Am 04.04.2025 veranstaltete das von der Deutschen Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG) geförderte Projekt <a href="https://oa-datenpraxis.de/">OA Datenpraxis</a> ein Webinar zum Thema “Offene Metadaten für Hochschulrankings am Beispiel des Leiden Ranking”. Für das Webinar konnten Nees Jan von Eck (CWTS Leiden) und Anja Oberländer (Universität Konstanz) als Vortragende gewonnen werden. Der Vortrag von Nees Jan van Eck bot Einblicke in die Hintergründe und Entwicklung des CWTS Leiden Ranking vom traditionellen Ranking hin zur Open Edition. Der Vortrag von Anja Oberländer komplettierte dies durch Schilderungen zur Anwenderperspektive des Leiden Ranking Open Edition am Beispiel der Universität Konstanz, insbesondere in Bezug auf die datengestützte Kommunikation der institutionellen Forschungs- und Open-Access-Erfolge nach innen und außen.</p>
<p>Dieser Beitrag fasst zentrale Punkte der beiden Vorträge sowie der anschließenden Frage-und-Antwort-Runde zusammen.</p>
<section id="leiden-ranking-open-edition" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="leiden-ranking-open-edition">Leiden Ranking (Open Edition)</h2>
<p>Nees Jan van Eck eröffnete das Webinar mit einer detaillierten Präsentation über die Entwicklung des Leiden Ranking Open Edition. Diese Initiative wurde von der strategischen Ausrichtung des CWTS zu <a href="https://www.cwts.nl/blog?article=n-r2q274">verantwortungsvollem Hochschulranking-Design</a> getragen. Im Gegensatz zum traditionellen Leiden Ranking, das auf proprietären Daten aus dem Web of Science von Clarivate basiert, erreicht die Open Edition vollständige Transparenz, indem sie auf OpenAlex setzt, einer vollständig offenen Datenquelle von <a href="https://ourresearch.org/">OurResearch</a>. Sowohl die zugrundeliegenden Daten als auch der Quellcode sind offen zugänglich, was es ermöglicht, die Publikationen zu identifizieren, die verschiedene Indikatorenwerte maßgeblich beeinflussen. Die bibliometrische Methodik ist größtenteils unverändert, um Vergleiche zwischen den beiden Ranking-Versionen zu ermöglichen. Der Vortrag addressierte auch Herausforderungen, wie z. B. eine unzureichende Datenabdeckung und -qualität, die bei der Verwendung offener Datenquellen auftreten können. Nees Jan van Eck betonte, dass die aktive Nutzung offener Daten nicht nur Probleme transparent macht, sondern auch rasche Verbesserungen durch einen community-basierten Ansatz ermöglicht.</p>
</section>
<section id="anwendung-des-leiden-rankings-an-der-universität-konstanz" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="anwendung-des-leiden-rankings-an-der-universität-konstanz">Anwendung des Leiden Rankings an der Universität Konstanz</h2>
<p>Anja Oberländer stellte die praktische Anwendung des Leiden Ranking Open Edition an der Universität Konstanz vor. Sie hob die bundesweit führende Position der Universität in der Open Access Dimension hervor und führte diesen Erfolg auf strategische Initiativen wie die zentrale Nutzung des institutionellen Repositoriums für Open-Access-Publikationen, die Pflege der Hochschulbibliographie und die Nutzung als Datenquelle für die Berichterstattung zurück. Darüber hinaus hat eine proaktive institutionelle Open-Access-Politik eine entscheidende Rolle gespielt. Die herausragende Platzierung der Universität in der Open Access Dimension ist daneben vor allem auf den hohen Anteil an Publikationen zurückzuführen, die über den grünen Weg des Open Access zugänglich sind. Der Vortrag addressierte auch die Herausforderungen der Universität Konstanz, diese Spitzenposition zu halten, da andere Einrichtungen zunehmend ähnliche Strategien verfolgen und verlagsseitige Open-Access-Veröffentlichungen verstärkt über Transformationsverträge ausgehandelt werden.</p>
</section>
<section id="diskussionspunkte" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="diskussionspunkte">Diskussionspunkte</h2>
<p>Im Anschluss an die Vorträge hatten die Teilnehmer:innen des Webinars die Gelegenheit, Nachfragen zu stellen. Interesse weckten beispielsweise folgende zentrale Punkte:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Datenquellen und Vergleichbarkeit: In der Diskussion wurde auf die Unterschiede zwischen OpenAlex, Scopus und Web of Science eingegangen. Es wurde hervorgehoben, dass OpenAlex eine breitere Abdeckung bietet. Trotz Unterschieden zwischen den Datenquellen ermöglicht die Verwendung der gleichen Methodik für die traditionelle und die Open Edition des Leiden Ranking einen Vergleich beider Versionen. Für die Open Access Dimension stützen sich alle Datenquellen auf Unpaywall, durch diesen gemeinsamen Referenzpunkt ist in diesem Aspekt bereits eine Vergleichbarkeit zwischen den Datenquellen gegeben.</p></li>
<li><p>Datenqualität und Einbindung der Community: Die Diskussion hob die Bedeutung des Feedbacks aus der Community bei der Identifizierung und Korrektur von Datenfehlern in OpenAlex wurde hervor. Probleme wie die falsche Klassifizierung von Publikationstypen und Fehler bei Affiliationsdaten konnten bereits durch entsprechende Rückmeldungen an OpenAlex verbessert werden.</p></li>
<li><p>Institutionelle Strukturen und ROR: Die Komplexität von institutionellen Strukturen und ihre Abbildung im Research Organisation Registry (ROR) wurde diskutiert. CWTS korrigiert Fehler im ROR manuell und fügt zusätzliche Beziehungen für die Nutzung im Leiden Ranking hinzu. Die community-basierte Kuratierung von ROR Daten trägt ebenfalls zur Verbesserung der Genauigkeit bei.</p></li>
<li><p>Verwendung von Ranking-Daten: Es wurde betont, dass die Daten des Leiden Ranking Open Edition zur Nachnutzung offen zugänglich sind. Sie können über eine Google Big Query-Instanz oder ein Webinterface abgerufen werden, wodurch die Nachnutzung für Nutzende mit unterschiedlicher technischer Versiertheit ermöglicht wird. Die Einrichtungen wurden ermutigt, mit den Daten basierend auf ihren spezifischen Interessen zu experimentieren.</p></li>
<li><p>Indikatoren: Es wurde darüber diskutiert, wie man über die traditionellen Metriken hinausgehen kann, die im Zuge von Reformen der Forschungsbewertung kritisiert werden. OpenAlex bietet eine gute Grundlage für die Weiterentwicklung, beispielsweise durch die Berücksichtigung nicht-englischsprachiger Publikationen und anderer Arten von wissenschaftlichem Output.</p></li>
<li><p>Open-Access-Strategien: Die Bedeutung einer umfassenden Unterstützung für Forscher:innen, die Förderung von Diamond Open Access und ein ganzheitlicher Ansatz anstatt einer Fokussierung ausschließlich auf quantitative Maßnahmen wurden als Schlüsselstrategien zur Erreichung von “Exzellenz” im Bereich Open Access hervorgehoben.</p></li>
<li><p>Vollständigkeit der Hochschulbibliographie: Auf die Frage nach der Vollständigkeit der Hochschulbibliographie an der Universität Konstanz und der Möglichkeit, dieses Vorgehen auf größere Universitäten zu übertragen, antwortete Anja Oberländer, dass die Bibliographie in den Naturwissenschaften sehr vollständig ist, während es in den Geisteswissenschaften Lücken gibt. Diese sind oft auf mangelndes Engagement der Forscher:innen zurückzuführen. Größere Universitäten können dieses Vorgehen zwar übernehmen, müssen jedoch mit einem höheren Zeitaufwand und mehr Ressourcen rechnen.</p></li>
<li><p>Kommunikation der Ranking-Ergebnisse an die Hochschulleitung: Auf die Frage, ob die Universität Konstanz das Ranking aktiv in die Hochschulleitung einbringt, um für Open Access zu werben, erläuterte Anja Oberländer, dass dies nicht nötig ist, da die Hochschulleitung den Wert von Open Access bereits anerkennt und die Ergebnisse aktiv nutzt. Die kleine Größe der Universität erleichtert dies.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="materialien-zum-webinar" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="materialien-zum-webinar">Materialien zum Webinar</h2>
<p>Die Folien der beiden Vorträge sind unter folgenden Links verfügbar:</p>
<ul>
<li>CWTS Leiden Ranking Open Edition: <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15147838" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15147838</a></li>
<li>Leiden Ranking at the University of Konstanz: <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15593872" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15593872</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="weitere-informationen-zu-oa-datenpraxis" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="weitere-informationen-zu-oa-datenpraxis">Weitere Informationen zu OA Datenpraxis</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.oa-datenpraxis.de">OA Datenpraxis</a> ist ein gemeinsames DFG-Projekt des <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de">Instituts für Bibliotheks- und Informationswissenschaft der Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin</a>, des <a href="https://os.helmholtz.de">Helmholtz Open Science Office</a> und der <a href="https://www.sub.uni-goettingen.de">Niedersächsischen Staats- und Universitätsbibliothek Göttingen</a>.</p>
<p>Weitere Informationen zu OA Datenpraxis finden Sie auf der <a href="https://oa-datenpraxis.de/events.html">Webseite</a> des Projektes.</p>
<p>Dieser Text - mit Ausnahme von Zitaten und anderweitig gekennzeichneten Teilen - ist lizenziert unter der <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
<div id="ref-oberlander_leiden_2025" class="csl-entry">
Oberländer, Anja. 2025. <span>“Leiden Ranking at the University of Konstanz.”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15593872">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15593872</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-van_eck_cwts_2025" class="csl-entry">
Van Eck, Nees Jan. 2025. <span>“<span>CWTS</span> Leiden Ranking Open Edition.”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15147838">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15147838</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{dörner2025,
  author = {Dörner, Sophia},
  title = {Rückblick: {OA} {Datenpraxis} {Webinar} Zu Offenen
    {Metadaten} Für {Hochschulrankings} Am {Beispiel} Des {Leiden}
    {Ranking}},
  date = {2025-06-11},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/21rye-3j054},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-dörner2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Dörner, Sophia. 2025. <span>“Rückblick: OA Datenpraxis Webinar Zu
Offenen Metadaten Für Hochschulrankings Am Beispiel Des Leiden
Ranking.”</span> June 11, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/21rye-3j054">https://doi.org/10.59350/21rye-3j054</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-06-11-Rueckblick-OA-Datenpraxis-Webinar-zu-offenen-Metadaten-fuer-Hochschulrankings/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jun 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-06-11-Rueckblick-OA-Datenpraxis-Webinar-zu-offenen-Metadaten-fuer-Hochschulrankings/logo_oa_datenpraxis(2).png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
